welcome to this data engineering crash
course created by Justin Chow this
course covers the essentials of data
engineering you'll learn about databases
Docker and analytical engineering you'll
explore Advanced topics like data
pipeline building with airflow and
you'll engage in batch processing with
spark and streaming data with Kafka the
course culminates in a comprehensive
project putting your skills to the test
in creating a full endtoend pipeline hey
everyone welcome to the course my name
is Justin Chow I'm a developer Advocate
at airbit I'm going to be going through
kind of essentially what you need to
know in order to become a data engineer
what goes into Data engineering and then
this is going to go into a fully fledged
demo where you can follow me in creating
a data pipeline from scratch and then
evolving that into a fully fledged data
pipeline using open-source tools such as
airbit so hopefully you enjoyed this and
this gathers some interest if anything
along with data engineering or software
engineering in general is of interest to
you then this should be good to know but
without further Ado let's get into the
course so we're looking over the
introduction to data engineering but you
may be thinking why data Engineering in
the first place well there's a couple
reasons why you may want to consider
getting into Data engineering first
there's a high failure rate of Big Data
projects and the percentage there based
off of the data that we've collected is
85 to 87% of those projects failing and
obviously as I've said that's pretty
pretty high those failures are due to
unreliable data infrastructures and
quality data in the past there's been an
expectations for data scientists to
build out that data infrastructure
that's necessary for those projects with
the infrastructure that was put in place
there's always incorrect data modeling
and redundant work that they have to do
because of the incorrect data modeling
and the Redundant work that they have to
do there's a high rate of data scientist
turnover so there's a high need of data
Engineers to process that data and
extract value instead of the data
scientists with all of that being said
there is a growing importance of the
data engineering role as we speak if
we're talking compensation right now in
the US the average median salary for
data Engineers is 90 to 150k a year and
obviously I say in the US it still
highly depends on the location and
whether you're in the states or not so
that number will change now let's look
at the business potential and impact
that data Engineers can have in any
company you will have a crucial role in
the success of making datadriven
decisions in the AI and ml space for
applications especially esally with the
rise of chat GPT right now and the AI
space in general data Engineers are
going to have that crucial role in
determining what happens with those
applications and the data in general now
let's look at the business potential
that you have as data engineers and the
impact you can make in any company that
you work for the first one being is that
you're going to have a crucial role in
the success of making data driven
decisions in the AI and ml space for
applications and so with the rise of
chpt and the AI space you're going to be
a crucial factor in that aspect and for
any company that wants to and should be
getting into AI in general the next
thing you're going to be doing is
ensuring that there's efficient
management and processing of the actual
data as it moves Downstream while it
moves Downstream you're also ensuring
that the data quality the security and
availability of it to those teams
Downstream such as the data scientists
the data analysts or any other team that
has to work with data in your company
that it's quality it's secure it's
formatted the way that they need it and
it's never not flowing Downstream this
will also lead to better insights and
outcomes for your company and overall
just drive Innovation and
competitiveness so that your company can
Thrive and that your team can Thrive so
now we're moving on into the first
module which is the introduction to
Docker and what we use Docker for in
data engineering but first we have to
have a better understanding of what it
is if you haven't used it before Docker
is an open source platform that
simplifies the process of building
shipping and running any applications
inside containers so imagine you are
working on a project and you want your
co-workers to try and use it to see if
there's any issues but they can't run it
for some reason and you kind of run into
that good old saying of hey it runs okay
on my machine well what Docker is able
to do is you're able to put your
environment into a container and that
container will include every dependency
and kind of Silo everything into again
this container which you can then pass
on to your co-workers or even even run
up in the cloud to have your application
running as it was when you were
developing it so it essentially just
helps organize and make sure everything
works as developed so if we're going
over containers and their benefits
containers are lightweight portable and
self-sufficient environments that
package an application along with all
its dependencies libraries and
configurations as I mentioned before
again just going over how much Docker
has really really helped engineers in
General on packaging their applications
to make sure that they don't run into
any issues down the line when testing
and developing and to make sure that
those environments are reproducible in
case anything goes wrong and making sure
that also when they're pushing up into
the cloud or into production that those
applications are working as intended and
when they were testing it's going to
work the same way in prod so now just
imagine that all your apps code and all
your apps dependencies are landing into
one of these containers and you're
shipping one of those off out into you
know your cooworker place or on AWS or
gcp everything that was inside that
container will be seen on the other end
as well now as I mentioned before in
software development we're looking at
Docker in the form of testing deployment
for its ease of use speed and
flexibility it assists with the
deployment scaling and management of
those applications using what we call
containerization which is just a
lightweight form of virtualization so if
you look on the right hand side's
illustration here you can see that we
have a couple apps that are in
containers using Docker uh as well as
you know sitting on top of your
operating system and the infrastructure
and it's all running all within the
docker ecosystem now there are three
main concepts with Docker that we need
to understand the first one is going to
be Docker files the second one is going
to be Docker images and the third one is
going to be Docker containers now let's
go over what those three are right now
the first step is the docker file the
docker file is a text file that consists
of all the instructions needed hence
blueprints that we want Docker to use
all in order to create the docker image
so the docker image is what is created
from the docker file hence the blueprint
so the blueprint then creates our Docker
image which is the lightweight
Standalone executable package that
includes everything we need to run your
piece of software that includes code the
runtime libraries environment variables
and config files the one thing to note
is that images are readon and immutable
so nothing can change within the docker
image itself if you wanted to create
another Docker image or modify anything
that exists you want to modify your
Docker file and the instructions that
inside that text file to create a new
Docker image so that's why we stick the
image into a Docker container which is
the runtime instance of our Docker image
or in other words the running version of
the image is the docker container this
Docker container is completely isolated
from the host and other containers that
you may have running it has its own file
system and can be started stopped and
deleted inde dependently so for example
we may have one Docker image that
contains our application but we have
three different Docker containers
running that same image so we have three
different environments three different
instances of that image but I can stop
one and the other two are still going to
run I can delete one and nothing changes
in those other containers because they
are isolated environments and you can
run tests you can do anything you want
in those containers but nothing will
change unless it is done inside the
container so first things first to get
started with Docker is obviously we're
going to want to install Docker so head
over to doer. and here is the landing
page of Docker now what we want to do is
simply just download Docker for whatever
operating system you have I am currently
running on a mac Apple chip so I would
click this and download Docker desktop
which also comes with Docker compose
which we will also need for later along
in this course but just know that Docker
compose and Docker desktop are two
prerequisites to running with Docker
right now now if you're on Windows
obviously follow the instructions for
Windows if you're on Linux follow the
instructions for Linux but go ahead and
download Docker for your machine and if
you have any questions uh you can also
go over to Docker and they have a really
good explanation in their docs on how to
install Docker desktop for your machine
and get going with that so make sure you
do this first now that we have Docker
installed I think the docker docks have
a great getting started guide on how you
can actually containerize an application
and so what we're going to do is
actually just go through this really
quickly and it can give us a great idea
of how to containerize an application
through a Docker file how we build the
image getting the image to run inside of
a container and then a couple other
things like networking and things like
that so let's go ahead and go through
the getting started guide and then we'll
move on into the SQL module right after
so if you were still confused on what a
container is or what an image is it
gives you a good rundown here at the
beginning of part one but let's go into
part two on how we can containerize an
application first things first is they
actually have a getting started app
which is just a to-do app for you to
containerize but what we're going to do
first is simply just clone this and and
use it for the rest of this guide I'm
going to open up my terminal here and
make a directory and I'm going to call
this Docker tutorial and I'm going to CD
into Docker
tutorial and then after that what we're
going to do is paste in the command that
was in there which simply just clones
the repo and obviously if it wasn't
clear enough and make sure you have a
text editor installed I'm using vs code
and I think that should be it obviously
Docker installed now that it's clone
let's go ahead and CD into the getting
started guide and what we can see here
is if we open up vs code there's a
couple things here so we have a spec
file we only really need to look at the
source file but this is just a simple
Todo app so let's go ahead and go back
to the getting started guide and it has
the instructions for you on Mac and
windows so depending on your operating
system make sure you follow the right
ones but we've already cded into it what
we're going to do is inside of the route
directory of the getting started app
we're going to to create a Docker file
and as mentioned before this is going to
be the instructions on how we build the
image that containerized the application
that the docker file is sitting in so
now that I've created the docker file if
type in LS you can see that the docker
file is there so what we're going to do
is they've provided us the instructions
or the contents that we're going to use
for this Docker file now you can see
that we have a couple things here that
we haven't seen before but essentially
what from is is we're going to use the
node 18 package that we're pulling from
the docker Hub to run our environment in
or our run time the working directory is
going to be in the SL app or the root
directory of the application this simply
copies everything and then we're going
to run this command which is yarn
install production other commands that
are going to be is going to be node and
we're going to look at in the source
index.js file and we're also exposing
Port 3000 so you can see that these
instructions are pretty straightforward
read like English the one thing to take
in mind is that this does have to be in
order this cannot be misplaced so keep
that in mind when you're writing your
own Docker files but what we're going to
do is we're simply just going to copy
this switch back over to our VSS code
head into Docker file and then just
paste this in and save now that that's
saved they give us a command so we're
going to run Docker build hyphen T which
simply just tags our image and then
we're going to name it getting started
so that will be the name of our image
and then the dot we need at the end to
tell Docker where to look for everything
to containerize which will simply just
be in the the current directory so I'm
going to go ahead and copy this command
as well paste this in also make sure
that you have the docker Damon running
if you installed Docker desktop just
simply open the application let
everything launch and then you should be
good so I'm going to go ahead and hit
enter this is going to do a couple
things awesome so now if we go back into
Docker desktop and we go into images you
can see at the very top getting started
is created we have an image the tag is
going to be the latest tag hasn't been
used yet tells us our size but now we
have an image with everything as you can
see from the docker file so you can see
the commands that we ran we have node
version 18 which we did with the from
command and then we're also exposing
Port 3000 so you can see that the docker
files blueprint is in play here next
thing we're going to do is going to
start this container so we can say
Docker run which is going to run the
image in a container we're going to flag
it for DP which the D flag is short for
detach which runs the container in the
background the P flag is short for
publish which means that we're creating
this Port mapping so that we can
actually access this container locally
and with the mapping we're pointing it
to a local host here so 12.0.0 point1
and we're opening it on Port 3000 now
keep in mind this can change say you
have an application already running on
Port 3000 but you wanted to run this on
Port 6000 you can definitely change this
but this number after the colon needs to
stay at 3,000 because in our Docker file
we exposed Port 3000 so to be able to
access this we need to still keep that
number to 3,000 and then after this this
is the name of our container so
obviously we're going to name it getting
started so let me copy and paste this go
back in our terminal and as you can see
it spits out a container ID uh I'm going
to go Ahad and copy this for later but
if we go back into Docker desktop now
just for a simpler gooey to see if we go
to the containers tab you can see that a
container was created with the image
getting started and it is currently
running on Port 3000 so now if we're
going to go back here and we want to go
to local poost Port 3000 you can see
that the app is now running locally and
we're accessing this container so that
is good now we can move on well first of
all what we may want to do is I can show
you guys that you can actually write
stuff to this so as I mentioned before
this is a to-do app so I can say get cat
food take out the trash very simple
react app going on right now that is
inside of a container so as I mentioned
previously before we started this demo
is that Docker contains a runtime it
contains all the environment variables
and it contains every single dependency
that react or this application in
general needs in order to run and so
we're siloed inside of a container with
a runtime with this environment and
we're able to actually use the
application within the container there's
a couple other commands it tells us so
in the command line we can run Docker PS
and it will name any other containers
that are currently running along with
their container ID so as I mentioned
this container ID popped up but if I
type in Docker PS it's going to be the
only one running but if there were any
other containers running we can pull
their container ID along with their
names and other information the other
thing to note too is that container IDs
can be accessed you don't need the full
container ID you only need the first
couple digits here and you can still
access that container so let's move on
to part three here now we were going to
want to make some changes to this code
and this is going to show us how
updating the application itself changes
things so they want us to change a
paragraph inside of the SRC static JS
app.js file so let's head back into vs
code so we're in SRC we're in static
we're going to go to
index.js JS app.js sorry and then go to
56 and then we're simply going to change
this text to be what they told us we're
going to go ahead and save that but now
that we've updated the application that
means we actually have to build another
version of this image because the image
we built cannot be Rewritten it is
completely readon and so if we're going
to make any changes we have to create
another image and so that's exactly what
we're going to do we're going to run the
same Docker build command command in the
terminal and that's going to build
another image and so now what we're
going to do is we're going to run
container command but we're going to get
an error here because we already have a
container with that name that's binded
to Port 3000 now if we want to remove
the old container that this will bring
us back into Docker PS so we're going to
run Docker PS and so we can see that
this container is still running so what
we're going to do is we're going to say
Docker RM paste the container ID and
that should give me another error saying
you cannot remove a running container so
we're going to say Docker RM and put in
the F flag that will stop the container
as well as remove the container so I'm
going to do that and that should now get
rid of it and now we can see that this
has stopped and we can copy and paste
this again and now we've created another
container and it has started running
with the updated image now if we go back
into the to-do app and refresh this you
can see that it's completely fresh and
the new text has been added so that's
what happens when you go and update an
application we're going to skip part
four but if you wanted to push this
image up into the docker hub for other
people to access you can absolutely do
that we're not doing that right now so
at your own you can go through part four
but we're going to go to part five and
this is actually a big one because
sometimes we're messing with data and as
we saw in the to-do app we have data and
we want to persist it but if we were to
stop the container and open it the data
that we had previously is going to be
gone so the way we can actually assist
data is by simply adding a couple things
so we're going to go through the steps
one more time but we're going to run
this command here we're simply going to
start a container that has a buntu
running and it's going to contain a file
called data. text that will have a
random number between 1 and 10,000 so
let's go open up my terminal and we're
going to run Docker through that and as
you can see it created another container
has an image of auntu I already had it
installed locally but if you do not have
the iunu image it will immediately
detect that and download that from the
docker Hub once we have that going we're
going to copy and paste this and this
will simply check the file that is
inside the container which is data. text
and it should spit out the name of the
or should not spit out the name but it
should spit out the number and what we
need to do is we need to remove the
current container ID or the placeholder
there with the actual container ID and
there we go we have 848 that's spit out
to us so we know that there is data in
side they want us to start another
container that has a bunu so we're going
to go ahead and do that as well and
it'll list in every single folder that
is currently in the root of that
container and then what we're going to
do also is we're going to remove that
first container so again we're going to
go Docker
RMF and then the first container should
be this one right here so we went ahead
and removed that so the way to process
data in that container is going to be by
creating a volume and it's pretty simple
to do so the first thing we're going to
do is run this Command right here that
they give us essentially we're going to
be creating a volume called Todo hyphen
DB so let me go ahead and open my
terminal here and what we're going to
see in the volumes tab now is a to do I
DB what we're going to have to do is
remove the container that we created
because it is running without a
persistent volume because we created the
volume after container creation so we're
going to have to create a fresh one so
again let me grab the the container ID
of the getting started container and
same thing Docker RM hyphen f and with
the container ID and that should remove
it for other purposes let me also just
remove this as well cool so we have a
clean slate now we're simply going to
copy this command but there's a couple
things here so along with the run and
run command the dnp flags as well as
mounting this or not mounting this but
binding it to the port 3000 we're also
mounting the volume here here which is
going to be the flag here that we see or
the option and we're specifying the
volume that we want to mount so the type
is going to be volume the source of the
volume is going to be the to-do hyphen
DB volume we just created and the target
is going to be where the actual data
sits inside of the container so that is
the path that we're going to do and then
getting started we're actually just
specifying the image that we we're using
or the container so let me go ahead and
copy this command paste it in and now
you can see that we have another
container with getting started and it
will be utilizing the 2db volume that
we've created so now what we can do
since it's running we're going to go
back here to the to-do app and as you
can see I have some data that was in
there and I didn't add anything you saw
that it was empty and there's two tasks
in here that I added previously about I
mean yesterday and they persisted so now
we're able to tap into the volume and
the data and anything that we do from
here on out let's just say I I don't
know go to the gym we want to add that
if we stop this container container and
then start it again and refresh this we
can see that the data is persisting now
so volume creation is going to be the
way to persist databases especially if
you're testing stuff this is a good way
to do that within Docker and it's easy
to play around with servers and actual
databases now that we have data that
persists instead of having to reload and
add more data over and over and over
again so there's a couple other things
that we can see but if you were to run
Docker volume inspect on the volume
itself you can see a couple things of
metadata here but specifically we get to
see the mount point the name the scope
of it and it's created time so those are
a cool couple things if you want to
persist databases within Docker next
thing we're going to do is we're going
to skip over to part seven I don't
really want to touch into the used bind
mounts right now but multicontainer apps
so as I mentioned we may have a couple
things that we're running and so
multiple containers are going to be
needed in this case we have our to-do
app but we also want to create a my sqil
container that runs in tandem with the
to-do app so that we can isolate our
database and our front an app here in
order for these two containers to talk
we're going to need to create a network
and that's exactly what we're going to
do right now so we're going to run this
command Docker Network create and the
Network's name is going to be to-do app
so let me go ahead and run that right
now it's going to give me an error
because I already created this but go
ahead and run that and it will create a
network there for you so now what we're
doing is we're going to create another
container and then attach it to the
network that we just created and so you
can see that we have a couple Flags here
first ones are going to be the network
so we're tying the network of this
container to the to-do app Network we
created the Alias of this is going to be
my SQL so when we see the container
through the network we're going to know
that this container here is the MySQL
container some of the variables that we
have here are going to be the volume
that we want to create is going to be
the to-do MySQL hyphen data volume so
we're creating a volume there to persist
the actual database and then we have two
environment Flags specific to my SQL
again if you're using something like
maybe say postgress there's going to be
some different environment variables you
need to attach to this container two of
the first ones being in my SQL are going
to be the root password as well as the
database name so we know that our
password Here is secret and then the
name of our database is going to be
to-dos and we're going to be pulling the
MySQL version 8 Docker image so what
we're going to do is copy this over and
we're going to go into our terminal and
create that and now we can see we have a
MySQL image again I've downloaded
locally already and the container is now
running to confirm that we have the
database running we're going to this
command here so we're exing hyphen it
and the container ID will go right after
that then it will spit out the my SQL
command enter in the user which is root
and then ask us for the password so let
me go ahead and copy this really quick
in here and copy the container ID that
it gave us and now replace the
placeholder enter It'll ask us for the
password and as we saw before it was
secret so let me enter that in and now
we are inside of our mySQL database the
next thing it asks us to do is type in
show databases to confirm that our
databases was created and we see the
to-dos database is here so our commands
ran successfully now we can say exit and
now we have a to-dos database we're
going to skip this part because it's not
really necessary but if you want to
follow it it simply just spins up a DNS
tool that will allow you to see the IP
address of the container and show you
that each container has its own IP
address so this networking step really
is crucial for these two containers to
talk to each other so what I'm going to
do here is I'm actually going to first
remove the container of the getting
started app that we created first
because it's not tied to this network
yet so let me go ahead and remove it
first and then we're going to create
another one using this command here and
as you can see we're doing the same run
command here but with a couple other
flags so there's just you know we're
tying it to the network here there's a
couple other environments like hooking
it up to the mySQL database so that
we're actually able to push data to the
database same thing with the node
versions and then initializing the
application with yarn install and and
run Dev so let me go ahead and copy and
paste this over and there we go we
should have another container built with
the note 18 Alpine image instead now if
we want to connect to the mySQL database
let's go ahead and do that here so we're
going to copy this command again copy
and paste this and then we need to get
into the mySQL database so let me copy
and paste that
enter the password here and it is secret
so now that we're in so we're going to
do the select function here and we're
going to select all from to doore items
and we can see that the three items that
we created inside of the application are
now here inside of the database so we're
confirming that the data that we created
in the volume is now inside of our my
SQL database and that right there is the
power of networking earlier in this
module I also mentioned Docker composed
and it makes this whole process that we
just did with this application 10 times
easier again as I mentioned before also
is that Docker compose is a tool that
helps you to find and share multiple
container applications and so we're
going to be doing that right now this
right here was the old command that we
had to run inside of our terminal to get
everything running for the MySQL and to
do app but we can simply do that all of
this in one Docker file and the docker
file now changes to a Docker composed.
yl file or you can shorten it to compose
y so we're going to head back into our
terminal here and inside of the rout
where we initially put our Docker file
we're going to create a new file and
call it compose do yaml and what Docker
has provided us with were a couple
things so we're going to go ahead and
copy and paste this now make sure it
added to space here but it will air out
if it has an empty space so cover that
space again yaml is very strict with
spacing and indentation so keep that in
mind but the first thing here we're
going to do is specify Services of our
compose file the first one is is going
to be our app which is going to contain
the image of the node version 18 so
we're going to run node in this
container next thing we're going to do
is add the command so the command we
want to run is going to be the yarn
install and and run the dev environment
there so we're going to add that here
next thing is we're going to open up the
ports and it's going to be the same port
the 127 on Port 3000 so now we're moving
the working directory to the volume
mapping uh and by doing that we're going
to add the working directory and then
the volumes so let me go ahead and add
that as well and then finally we're
going to add the environments so these
environment variables are all going to
be the MySQL environment variables so
that we can access the database through
the application itself when we add a
need todos so again the host the user
password database name these are all
there and are going to specified for
this app container now we're going to do
the same but for my SQL so we saw the
app container but now if we back up a
couple spaces we're going to add the
MySQL container so you can see that
these two are on the same line one being
app with all of its information here and
then MySQL will contain the same but now
we're pulling the MySQL version 8 image
the volumes that we want to use for this
container is going to be the to-do MySQL
data so let me go ahead and add that and
then the overall volumes here are going
to be outside of that and then finally
what we need to do is we're going to add
the environment variables for the
specific container so we can access
now everything in your composed. file
should look like this again the top
level is identifying what services that
we want this file to create the first
one being our app container using the
node 18 image this is the command we
want to run this is the port that we
want to expose and use to access this
application our working directory is
going to be this root directory that
contains everything here the volumes
we're mapping is going to use the app
this is the environment variables we use
to connect to our MySQL container that
also contains its own information and so
now it's much easier with Docker compose
to run this application now that we have
our composed. yl file I can open up my
terminal here let me exit my SQL clear
this now all I have to do is run Docker
compose up and I can add The Hyphen D
flag to make sure that this runs in the
background and what that's did just now
was literally spit out two containers
one it looks like it failed because I
have a container running already that
has 3,000 so let me go ahead and just
delete this and delete this from the
docker desktop app so we can have a
clean slate and let me run the same
thing and there we go now it's spit out
the getting started app and it contains
our app and my SQL container both of
them running and we have opened on Port
3000 and if I head over into our Local
Host Port 3000 I'm refreshing and you
can see it's all fresh so we are no
we're using a different volume here but
the application is now running
successfully it is attached to our mySQL
database and we can continue and now add
data here that will persist because we
have tied a volume here to both of these
containers now if we wanted to tear it
down all we would have to do is Docker
compose down and that will shut down and
stop our containers from running and
that right there is a simple rundown of
how you can create images and a
container through Docker using Docker
files or a composed. yl file and then
accessing those containers to do certain
things we ran a application in the form
of a to-do app and we also created a
mySQL database pretty quickly here in
their own environments and that way we
have co-workers that are working on the
same thing they can run the same image
that we're on using the same environment
variables using the same dependencies
and essentially be able to recreate any
problems or just have the same
environment that we're running on every
single time and that is the power of
containerization through Docker we're
going to be using a lot of these skills
in the coming lessons so hopefully that
helps but now let's move on to the SQL
module where we're going to be using SQL
but we're also going to start our own
little database inside Docker as well so
let's get to it so now that we have
Docker set up and we know the basics
we're going to move it on to SQL or SQL
however else you want to call it but SQL
stands for structured query language
it's a standard language used for
database creation and manipulation
databases like MySQL or postgress use
SQL for you to query any of the data
within their own tables so let's go
ahead and start our playground we're
going to set up a database using
postgress within a Docker container and
then we can create our own tables with
fake data to play around with and we'll
use them later on in the course as well
all right so first things first is I
have a terminal open and I've created a
data engineering database directory
because we're using Docker we do not
have to install postgress locally what
we can do is run the command Docker pull
postgress and what that's going to do is
look up the image of postgress on the
docker Hub pull the latest version of
that down and now we can actually create
a container that's running the postest
image so now we got to start our postest
container now that we have the image so
I'm going to say Docker run the name of
this container is going to be data
engineering postgress uh the environment
variables that we that I want are going
to be related to postgress which is
going to be
postgress password and what that's going
to be is just going to be
secret and then I'm going to do the D
flag and we're going to say we're going
to use the postgress image go ahead and
run that now I have my container now
what I want to do is I want to create a
new database inside of postgress so I'm
going to say Docker exec hyph U for the
user which is just postgress as default
the name of the container which is just
data engineering of
postgress going say create DB
and the name of the database is going to
be
postgress
DV now that we've run that we've created
a sample database inside now let's go
ahead and connect to it so I'm going to
say Docker
exec
slit data
engineering
postgress
psql hyphen U for the user on postgress
and the name of the database which is
going to be
postgress now we are inside as you can
see of the postgress database if I do
/dt no current tables as of right now so
that's exactly what we're going to do
we're going to create our first table I
have these commands already written out
so I don't waste as much time so the
first thing I'm going to do just for an
example is create a table called users
so inside this command you see a couple
things so we have an ID of the type
serial which is also our primary key
here as an identifier we have a first
name which is at most 50 characters we
have a last name which is the same thing
we have an email that is also characters
but we want it to at least be 100 and
then we have a date of birth which is
just in the type of date so we're going
to hit enter it's going to show us that
we have a table so now if I do /dt we
can see that the users table is now
created and populated inside of this
database I'm going to go ahead and copy
in some fake data as well and don't
worry this will all be in the
description below so that way you can
copy and paste this in as you follow
along so I'm going to and copy and paste
this and this is simply just user so it
contains a first name a last name an
email and date of birth so let me go
ahead and enter and you can see it
entered in 14 records so now this brings
us into the First Command we're going to
learn so the First Command we're going
to want to learn is the select command
and it's pretty self-explanatory as you
saw already we entered in 14 rows of
data and if I wanted to select anything
from that table I'm going to need to use
the select command so I'm going to say
select and I'm going to add this
asterisk what the asterisk typically
means is a wild card pretty much meaning
you want all of the columns within a
table so you can read this query as
select all now I'm going to add from and
then the last part of this is going to
be the table name so I'm going to say
users and do not forget this is very
important that every query needs to end
in a semicolon otherwise the query won't
go through so make sure you always add a
semicolon at the end of every query so
once I hit enter you're going to see
that I get back a formatted view of the
table that I just queried we saw before
that we entered in 14 rows of data and I
see that I get exactly 14 rows back all
having the ID first name last name email
and date of birth formatted in a much
more pleasing way than what we see up
here the select query is going to be a
frequently used command by everybody who
uses SQL so make sure you know it and
understand it but again very
straightforward another command that
gets used in conjunction with select is
also going to be distinct we use
distinct in conjunction with select if
we want a specified value within a very
particular column so let's say we want
every single email within the users's
table what we'll say is we're going to
say select
distinct email
from and then we're going to say users
table so again we're reading this back
if you haven't noticed already you
typically all the SQL commands are going
to be in all caps keep in mind you do
not need this but it is much easier and
it is probably best practice to
capitalize every command that is SQL and
lowercase everything that is either a
table or some type of value that you
need but if we're reading this back we
want to select distinct emails from the
user's table so again it reads just like
English we add the semicolon if we hit
enter it's going to give us just the
emails in every single distinct email
now keep in mind this is not in order
but we do get 14 rows of data back we
can see that the query was successful so
that's how you can select data from the
whole table to get a better view or
select distinct values within a
particular column but let's move on to
other commands so now that we have our
users table that has data that exists in
there what if we wanted to update some
information say an email if a user
changed their email or a date of birth
if they entered it wrong this is where
the update command comes in handy so
let's say for example if we go back up
to our table that we wanted to change
John's email so what we're going to do
is we're going to say update so the
query starts with update now after
update we're going to enter the table
name so we're going to say users and
then we're going to say set so now we
want to address what column and value we
want to change in the users table so
we're going to say email and then that's
going to equal whatever our value is
going to be inside of single quotes so
for example we can just say you know new
uncore mail@gmail.com
the problem with this query is if we
were to hit enter on this it would
change the emails for every single row
inside of the user's table which isn't
exactly what we want and if you were
doing this in a production database it
would probably go Haywire so how can we
modify this query for it to actually
only update one person's email inside
the table what we can do is introduce
the wear command so after we set the
email to the new value we're going to
say where and then we're going to say
first uncore
name so now we're saying where the first
name so we're selecting a particular
first name is equals to and the first
name in this case is going to be John
and we're going to hit a semicolon so
again we're going to backtrack here
we're going to update the users table
we're going to set the email so we're
selecting the column email to newor
mail@gmail.com
where are the first name is equals to JN
so that means that we're going to look
for JN inside of the first name column
once we find JN we're going to go to his
email and change the email over to the
new value so if I hit enter we can see
that we have one updated change now if I
say select go back to the cap select all
from users table we're going to see that
John's actually changed so he gets moved
down he still has an ID of one but his
email is now newor Emil mail.com so
again if we're using the update command
it's very helpful if anything changes in
terms of data and we need to update
something that's where we' use the
update command now let's say you wanted
to enter in new data into a table well
that's where the insert command comes in
if you're starting to see the pattern
here SQL commands are very
self-explanatory and the fact that they
read English and kind of like python so
if you want to insert new values you
would reach for the insert command so
we're going to create a new table called
the films table add some films and then
then show the insert command but go more
in depth into it all right so we are
back in our database and I have the
command here already I'm going to create
the table of films again so create table
is also a command that we didn't get
really into but again self-explanatory
we're just creating a table here called
films within the parentheses we're going
to see the film ID with a type we have a
title a release date a price which is
new that we're seeing a decimal type we
have a rating and then a user rating the
one thing to note within the user rating
is that we're checking to see if the
number value that goes into user rating
rating is greater than or equals to 1
and that the user rating is less than or
equals to 5 so obviously we want to go
between 1 and 5 here so if I hit enter
we're going to see that if I do /dt
which is like LS in a normal bash
terminal is kind of like listing every
table inside of a database we see that
the films table is now created so let me
go ahead and copy my insert command here
and we see that we have insert into so
again self-explanatory want to insert
values into the films table within the
first set of parentheses we see the
names of the columns that we want to add
and again those are fitting and matching
exactly what we have on this side right
here when we created the table after the
first set of parentheses we have a
values command and after that everything
inside of the parentheses are values
that have to match the order in which
you placed every single column so the
first one we have is a title which is
these are all not fake data but I have
them generated so we have Inception the
release date which is right here in the
date format we have its price in a
decibel format we have the rating of the
movie as well as the user rating of the
movie and so you can see it fits within
this set of parenthesis it fits the
order of this set of parenthesis so if
we hit enter right now you can see that
we've entered in 20 rows of data if I
say select
all from
films we can see that a little out of
place here because my terminal is a
little big but we can scroll down and we
can see that all the data was entered in
go ahead and skip this line let me make
it smaller so that we can see more of it
but if I hit that again we can see the
table is formatted properly the same way
that the user's table was but that right
there is how you can insert data into a
table it's doesn't have to be that big
every single time if we just wanted to
insert one more row it would just be the
exact query back here except just one
more line another really useful command
that you should know is going to be the
limit command imagine you have a
database that has thousands upon
thousands of Records but you only need a
certain amount so you want to limit the
query to that amount that's where limit
comes in so as we saw in the new films
table we saw that we have 20 rows but
what if we only want less than 20 so
let's say five that's where we would use
limit so let's do select
all from we're going to go into the
films table but after films typically we
would have that semicolon to end the
query but now we're going to add a limit
and then the value of what we want the
limit the query to so because we have 20
we want less than 20 here let's just say
I only want five records to come back if
I hit enter you're going to see that I
only get the first five records in the
table to come back so that is a very
easy easy to understand command here and
very useful to limit the amount of
records that come back cuz you could
imagine as I said before if you're
trying to query a database or a table
that has thousands of records that query
could take a very long time so if you
want that to speed up a little bit and
you only need a certain amount to see
what the data looks like if it's
formatted properly the limit command is
going to be your best friend the next
thing we're going to cover is going to
include some math here but we're going
to go over aggregate functions in SQL
aggregate functions in SQL allow us to
do computations on top of a single
column through every single row of a
table it's incredibly useful in data
analytics where it allows us to
calculate important metrics and gain
insights from our data so let's get into
the first one the first one is going to
be count now the count function allows
us to count the number of rows depending
on if it matches the condition that we
give it so now that we have our films
table let's say we wanted to count the
amount of films if we don't know how
many are inside the table let's start
the query here so let's say select right
after the select statement we would say
count in the parentheses we would count
however many we want but if I add an
asterisk here that's going to say count
every single record inside of this table
if it matches the condition I'm about to
give it so we're going to say count from
film's table so again this is selecting
the number of Records within this
condition here and what we give it is an
asterisk for all from the films and what
this should give me back is the number
20 because we have 20 rows inside this
column so just remember within this
parenthesis here is going to be the
condition depending on what that
condition is it will spit back to you
always a number depending on if it's
true within that condition and count is
really useful for that the next
aggregate function we're going to look
at is going to be the sum function now
we would use sum to calculate the sum of
all the numbers in a numeric column so
if we take a look here we have a prices
column so now if we wanted to let say
calculate the sum of every single price
in this column we would say select sum
inside the parentheses we would say
price because we want to use the price
column from the films table so now if we
look back at this we're selecting the
sum function is going to look into the
price column and add up every single
number value within it and it will spit
back to us the total sum of every single
movie that we have inside this table so
if you were to have gone to every single
one of these movies at this price you
would have spent
$228.8 now let's say we want to get the
average of something inside of our table
say for example we want the average user
rating of movies in this table well
that's where the average statement or
the average function comes in it's going
to look the exact same as the sum
function so we're going to say select
but instead of sum we're going to say
average or AVG and inside the
parenthesis we're going to enter in the
column that we want to take take a look
at which is going to be user uncore
rating close the parenthesis there and
then we're going to say from the films
table and that then gives us an average
of every single user rating that the
movies have which is going to be 4.6 and
lastly one of the more useful ones is
going to be Max and min max and Min are
used to find the highest and lowest
numeric value within a column so let's
look at our price column again if we
wanted to get the lowest and the highest
values in the prices column our query
would look something like select and
then we would say Max inside the max
column our condition would be the column
we want so we want price we're going to
add a comma here and we're going to say
Min again parenthesis and looking at the
prices
column from the films table now if I hit
enter here we're going to see the max
value here was $4.99 and the minimum was
$7.99 so the the cheapest movie out here
that was in the table was
$77.99 and the max was $4.99 so very
helpful to sift through a big table if
you're just trying to find the highest
value and the lowest value another
useful statement in SQL is going to be
group by we use Group by to get
identical data into groups it's also
typically used with aggregate functions
like the ones we just did like count sum
min max average so that we can group the
result sets into one or more columns
let's take a look at how this would look
if we were to use Group by with the
average aggregate function let's take a
look at the films table again and let's
say we want to group the average user
rating based off of the movie's actual
rating how would we do that we're going
to select the rating column here and
then we're going to add a comma and add
our aggregate function since we're
stringing together two selects and
inside the condition of the average
function we're going to put in the user
uncore rating
column from the films Table after that
we're going to say Group
by and what we wanted to group that by
is by the rating so we're going to get
the average of every user rating inside
of the film's table and then group the
results by each individual rating so we
have PG-13 we have R and we have G npg
so we should see four rows inside of the
results after I had enter you can see
the average rating for R-rated movies
was
4.61 the average rating for PG-13 is 4.5
PG was 4.8 and G was 4.4 so now you can
see how this could be useful to group
together identical forms of data and
compare them against each other this is
especially important in data analysis
again it allows us to organize the data
into a different way and then run
computation on top of that especially
with them being in groups it's also
important to note the order that we did
this query if we were to have switch the
rating and the average functions here we
would have got a different result so the
order of the the query does matter
depending on how you want to format your
data so keep that in mind one cool
feature you can do in SQL is join two
different tables that have different
data sets and get a result that combines
both of the data you need into a
formatted table there are two different
commands that we can use for this and
we're going to go over those right now
the first one being in join and the left
one being left join they do very similar
things but there are key differences
that make them unique so let's go over
what those are right now but before we
do that we're going to need to create
another table that we can use data
against alongside our existing films
table so let's first create the film
category table so I'm going to go ahead
and copy and paste this so we have a
category ID a film ID and the category
name these categories match every single
movie that we currently have inside of
the films table now I'm going to go
ahead and insert our values here so let
me go ahead and do that hit enter enter
we have 39 records here so now if I do
select all from the Filmore category
table now we can see that we have our
category IDs and we have our film IDs as
well as their category names go ahead
and Skip all these lines here so now we
have two tables that we can use to join
with each other if we want a table where
we have all the movies as well as the
film categories we're going to learn
about two things right now we're going
to learn about how in join works and
we're going to learn about how aliases
work in your SQL queries so let's go
ahead and get to that so in order to
understand how joins work we need to
First create some tables that go against
the data that we have currently in all
those tables and insert some new ones so
that we can join them together so the
first table we're going to create is
going to be the actor's table so this is
going to have an actor ID and the actor
name I'm going to have all the actors
from every single film that we have
currently and then we're also going to
create the film actors table and this
will make sense in a second so this one
is going to have the film ID and actor
ID as well as a primary key and now into
the actors table are going to go every
single name of each actor that are
associated with the specific films let
me go ahead and insert those and now we
also have the film actors which are
going to include their ID
as well as the film IDs so now you can
see that we have two separate tables
that we just created if I do select all
from the actors table we can see that we
have actor ID as well as the actor name
all in this table and then if we say
select all from Filmore actors table you
can see that we have a film ID and an
actor ID so this goes with multiple
different tables that we have
relationships with and now we can focus
on how to join all this data together
and make sense of inner join and left
join okay so like I said we're going to
focus on the inner join and we're also
going to add some aliases and what those
are going to look like let me copy and
paste this in here so we can go over
what this looks like first we have our
select statement and now we're going to
go into what we're selecting so we have
f. film ID and this will make sense in a
second we have f. tile we have a. actor
name so we're selecting the film ID
we're selecting the title name as well
as the actor name that's what the
results are going to look like now we're
going to select from the films table and
after the films table is a space and an
F so the Alias that we want to give our
films table is f so now that anytime we
want to access the films table all we
have to do is type f as we can see here
after we select the films table and add
the Alias we're going to do an add our
inner join statement this is where we're
going to add different tables and join
them together so after you say in join
we're going to take on the film actors
table and we're going to give it an
alias of fa so short for film actors and
we're going to join these two tables on
which is why we have on so we're going
to select the film's table and then the
film ID from the film's table if it
equals the same film ID from the film
actor's table that's where we're going
to join those rows and columns on we're
going to add another inner join we can
string on as many joins as we want so in
this this case we're going to do two
because we're bringing on the actor's
table so we're going to join the actor's
table and we're going to give it an
alias of a on the fact that any actor
IDs from the film actor table is also
equals to the actor IDs from the actor's
table and lastly we see order by that's
a statement we haven't gone over yet but
we're going to order them by the film
IDs from the film table so we're going
to order them by those film IDs but
we're going to go from the film table so
I know that's a lot to take in but let's
go over it one more time the final table
that we are going to see we're going to
have three different columns we're going
to see the film ID from the film's table
we're going to see the title from the
film's table and then the actor name
from the actor's table and now the
reason we're not seeing the film actor's
table in the select column is because
one we're using the film actor's table
as a bridge to connect the actor names
to their correct films that's what we
did here on the join as we took our film
actors and if we look up at the film
actors table we can see that we only
have a film ID and an actor ID each of
them are just numbers but they
correspond to an actor as well as a
movie so we took the data that we have
from the film actor table and we joined
it on top of the film table now if there
was a film ID that matches any of the
movies inside of the movies or I'm sorry
inside of the films table then we're
going to match those together take take
that data and use it for the results
section here now that bridge allows us
to say okay well now we want to join the
actors table on top of the film actor's
table now now we can associate actors
with the correct movies now that we have
the film IDs and the actors that go with
them so we're taking on the actor's
table in the form of or in the Alias of
a on top of film actors and now if we
have any actor IDs that match the film
IDs in the film ID or in the film actors
table we're going to take that data and
then use that here and then we'll
obviously again order them by the film
ID in the films table a lot to take in
again but if I hit enter we're going to
see that we have a very nice formatted
table here like I said we're ordering by
the f. film ID which we use up here as
well so everything is ordered
chronologically or you know in numerical
order 1 2 3 4 and then that film ID will
match Inception and then Leonardo
DiCaprio checks out was in Inception Tim
Robbins was in Shashank Redemption
Marlon Brando was in Godfather so you
can see on and on that this does make
sense and now if we were to go and do
select all from the films
table we can see that Inception had a
film ID of one so that checks out right
there um and then if we go to
select all from the actor's
table we can see that Leonardo DiCaprio
had an actor IDF one so all of that data
that we just took in actor idea of one
and film idea of one matches exactly
what it was between all the three
different tables that we had a
relationship with all to give us one
very nice table that we can now use for
any form of data analysis or what any
sort of computation that any of your
teams need and that's really a awesome
way to join multiple different tables
this was an example of inner join left
joins do something similar but there is
a catch between the two that make them
unique as I mentioned before so let's
take a look at what left joins look like
so in order for joins to make sense we
need to add another entry into the films
table so let's go ahead and do that I
have here a single entry that I will
copy and paste right now so I am simply
going back into the films table and
entering the mystical Adventures movie
so me go ahead and hit enter and then if
we do select all from films we can see
that the mythical Advent or mystical
Adventures is now added at the very
bottom so now we have 21 so now let me
copy the left join query that we want to
do here and now it's going to look very
similar to the inner join where we're
taking the film ID from the films table
the title from the films table and the
actor name from the actor's table again
we're adding the aliases here with the
letter f for the the film's table we're
left joining the film actors table again
using that as the bridge uh it's
essentially going to be the same query
but if we were to hit enter on this
right now you can see that we still do
have the table filled out properly and
formatted properly but we have mystical
Adventures but with no actor so the
thing with left joins is even if there
is a null value or it's missing a value
the result table will still show even if
there isn't an exact match now if we
were to go back up to the query where we
do the inner
join after we've now added the new movie
we can see that it doesn't show up so in
join if there is a null value and the
condition doesn't the condition isn't
fully met we will not see that in the
result table so for the result table you
see that we only have 20 entries as
opposed to the left join where we have
the 21 but we just have a missing actor
so to now show that this is actually
true we're going to insert a new Act
actor as well as the new actor IDs to
populate the movie so the movie we added
was a fictional movie so let's go ahead
and add the actor's name so we're going
to add Jane do and John Smith and we're
also going to add the film actors as
well so 21 and22 so if we were to run
our left join command again we're going
to see that mystical Adventures actually
does populate now but we're going to see
that the mystical Adventures actually
does populate now with the actor name
so this kind of just proves that no
matter what left joins will always show
the result table even if the conditions
aren't meant and there is a null value
there's two more commands we're going to
go over the first one is going to be
Union and the second one is going to be
Union all these do get a little mixed up
with the inner joint and left joint
since they kind of function the same way
in terms of how they work but they are
completely different and let's go over
what makes them unique here so the next
two commands are going to be Union and
Union all these are going to be the last
commands that we go over so we actually
use the union operator to string
together two select statements but with
the Union statement it actually removes
any duplicate rows with the same values
but with Union all you're going to get
duplicate rows in the result set table
so it kind of functions the same way as
in join and left join in terms of their
differences but the queries are going to
be very different so let's go ahead and
take a look at what that looks like all
right so back in the terminal we're
going to copy this Union command and
we're going to go over every single line
so with this command we're going to
select title as name from film so we're
going to use the name Alias we never use
the as operator it is completely
optional when giving aliases to use as
so you can omit this when doing it but
it makes a little bit more clear if we
say Select Title as name so instead of
the column being named title we're it's
going to be called name when we get the
result table from the films table and
then we're going to add the union
operator here and then string on on
another select statement so we're going
to select the actor name as name from
the actor's table and we're going to
order them by name so if I hit enter
here you're going to see that doesn't
really make too much sense but we can
see how it works kind of we have one
column since we named them both name
down here and we're putting down this is
an actor this is an actor this is the
name of the movie so we put together a
bunch of names and we order them
alphabetically by name now if we were to
do that again
but instead we were to change the actor
name to actor and hit enter and it would
be the same thing for Union all except
remember there are going to be duplicate
rows or duplicate values within here so
if we were to scroll down you can see
that we get Tom Hanks twice whereas in
the table above we only got Tom Hanks
once so again this is a prime example of
Union and Union all so we're putting
together all the data that we're
grabbing using two select statements
into one result table another cool
little thing you can do in SQL that's
actually going to be very useful later
down the line especially as a data
engineer is going to be something called
subqueries we've seen them a little bit
here by using the parentheses but let me
go ahead and show you what one looks
like and then we'll go over it so let me
copy and paste it over so as you can see
here we have first a select statement
where we're selecting the title now
inside of that we have a par or we have
a Comm and then inside a set of
parentheses we're using another select
statement but we're selecting the actor
name and again using aliases and a join
so from actors Alias of a we're joining
the film actors again using it as a
bridge and then the final result from
this select statement is going to be the
actor name and then we're pulling this
from films using the Alias F so this is
just a string select statement but a
subquery so before this finishes we're
going to run and find the title from the
films table but then we're also going to
look here SQL will go ahead and execute
this query and then add it into the
results table so right now what this is
doing is it's retrieving the films title
along with the name of one of its actors
so if we go ahead and hit enter you can
see that it's kind of the same thing
what we did earlier in the course where
we joined two different tables but we
used a subquery instead subqueries can
be used in multiple different ways we
saw this being used in the select Clause
here but we can actually use this also
with the in operator so if we wanted to
retrieve films that have either you know
let's say Leonardo DiCaprio or Tom Hanks
this is what the query would actually
look like so let me go ahead and show
you so we're selecting the title from
the films table where the film ID in and
then this is where our subquery would
start this is where we're going to say
hey we're looking for any films and
we're want the name of them if the
condition is met here where the actor's
name is either Leonardo Caprio or Tom
Hanks so we're looking for both of these
movies so we're going to say Obviously
go into the film actors table and do
another join here so we're adding that
condition by joining in other tables and
that's where subquery can really become
useful here so if I enter you're going
to see that we're only going to get the
titles back and Inception Force gum and
Toy Story are going to be the three
movies that contain Leonard DiCaprio or
Tom Hanks and obviously most of us have
seen that so that checks out but that is
a quick little intro and awesome little
thing we can do in SQL
subqueries all right so now that we've
gone through SQL we can finally get into
building our first data pipeline this is
going to evolve as the course progresses
but we're going to start off by building
this data pipeline from scratch using a
python script and moving data that way
we're also going to be using Docker to
host both of our source and destination
databases using postgress so you'll get
to see how this all coincides and works
together with Docker one thing to note
before we keep moving on is there is a
repo for this whole project you can see
it here with a read me on how to get
started and how everything works if you
go up here to the branches you can see
the evolution of this project so first
we're going to be starting with just the
main elt script and then we're going to
be adding on a Cron job to show
orchestration from there we're going to
be adding DBT to the mix which we'll get
into later and then also airflow and
then eventually air bite so there's
going to be this progression of the
course to show kind of how a main elt
script uh that's created manually would
look and then as we add in more open
source tooling you'll kind of see the
power of how everything works together
and why you know we are using these open
source tools in the first place so just
for your reference make sure to look in
the description and you can find this
link here to my GitHub repo with
everything you need to see just in case
you get stuck on something but for the
rest of this project I'm going to be
creating a new directory but it will
directly reference this project so just
keep an eye on this when you're working
through it all right so I have my
terminal open so let's go ahead and
create our first directory here I'm
going to say make and then for here I'm
going to say elt and then we're going to
CD into elt um and then from there we're
going to say touch
eltor
script.py let's also create a Docker
file so I'm going to use Docker compose
in this so I'm going to say Docker
compose and let's go ahead and open that
up okay so now you can see we have two
files that we just created we have the
elt script and then we also have the
docker compos file all empty but we're
going to fill this out now the first
thing we're going to do is actually fill
out this Docker compose file in order to
have the two databases that we need one
being our source where our data is
coming from and the destination where we
want to send data to so that way we can
use the alt script to move data between
those two now we're going to use
postgress for this example because we
can use it as an open source database
and so so let's go ahead and fill this
out so the first thing we need is going
to be the version and uh version three
is going to be what I'm going to be
using for the doc compos file now we
list our services so in here this is
where we name our first service and in
this case I'm going to name it Source
postgress that's going to be our first
service now remember with yo files it is
very crucial for you to have proper
spacing within the file itself if not
the yl file is not going to read
properly and it'll actually error out if
you don't follow the correct tabbing and
indentation so keep that in mind um so
the first thing we're going to do is
list the image and for the image here
I'm just going to say we want to pull
from dockerhub the postgress image and
the latest version of it so that way
we're always up to date the ports so
this is going to be very important for
us in terms of accessing the actual
service itself so with the source and
the destination databases we need to
expose the ports so that we can actually
access them on the local host and so for
this I'm going to say we're going to
open this up on
5433 and by default we need do 5432 I
believe so let's go ahead and do that
now for the networks we're going to
create a network for all of our
containers so you can look at all these
Services as a single container in each
single container contains an image that
the runtime is going to use and so we
actually need to create a network for
all of these different containers to
talk to now I'm going to name it _
Network and we will see that at the end
of this file we're going to have a well
I can actually just do this right now so
we're going to have a networks section
and in there we'll list the _ network we
also have to specify this is going to be
a bridge driver um you don't have to
worry about that what that means but
just know that within the network all of
the containers are going to recognize
that this is the network we wanted to
talk uh remember that is outside of the
services tab this is going to be its own
section here with its own properties so
make sure that you're doing that there
now within the source postest service
we're going to do some environment
variables here that are going to be very
important for the first one we're going
to do the
postgress database so this is going to
the name of our database and for the
name we're going to say sourcecore DB
keep it very simple uh the next one
we're going to do is going to be the
user so postgress user and this one let
me uh actually should be this way not an
equal sign it should be a colon my bad
this is going to be user postgress as
default and then obviously the next one
is going to be password this you can
change to however you want it to be I'm
going to say secret for this one and now
for the volumes this is going to make
way more sense and I I should actually
create this um this folder now but we're
going to create an elt folder we're
actually going to drag this elt script
into that folder just so we can have
some separation between everything the
docker composed file will remain in the
root but um for the next one we're going
to say volumes and if we remember what
we were talking about in the docker
section the volumes is how we were able
to persist data so each container can
create a volume and then whatever we're
doing inside of that Docker container
will contain the data that we're
utilizing within that volume so that
data will always persist as long as we
do not delete it from within Docker what
I'm going to do here is I'm going to
specify the path of so Source this will
make a lot more sense in a second so
Source IND justy uh init so we're
actually going to have some data that
we're going to initialize this postgress
database with and the init SQL folder or
file sorry that we're going to create
inside of the source DB in nit folder is
what we're going to utilize and so after
we've done that we're going to map this
uh so if you see the colon after this
this uh directory we're actually mapping
this to the directory within the docker
container so you could see this as this
is our local directory and we're going
to map this over into the docker
directory and where this is going to go
is going to go into the docker entry
point innit db. d/ init SQL okay so this
should be exactly what it looks like for
you and this is going to be the same it
pretty much looks identical so we're
actually going to do this and I'm going
to do shift option down to duplicate
this we're going to add a space here so
this is going to be our very first
service here which is going to be the
source database and now what we want to
create here is going to be the
destination database uh and we're going
to change the port here to
5434 we're going to keep this on the
network on the elt network now this also
needs to change so this is going to be
destination ZB we'll keep user and
password the same and we actually don't
want any volume section here why because
we don't want to save the data every
single time for testing purposes I want
to make sure that the elt script runs
every single time successfully and so if
the data persists I can't confirm or
deny that the elt script is actually
working so that every single time we
kill this Docker container I want the
data to vanish so that's what we're
doing here for the next service and the
last one we're going to do for this
section is going to be the elt script
now why do we need to create one here
well we need to create one in order for
Docker to see that we're actually
utilizing a script here to send data
from the source and destination
databases so we actually have to use
Docker for this and use it for the
runtime to actually run the script
itself instead of us having to manually
do it so what we're going to do here is
utilize the manual Docker files at the
same time of using Docker compos there's
different reasons for for doing this I
think it's just easier to run certain
commands utilizing it this way and we'll
actually see what what this is doing so
it's going to look a little different so
we're going to say build under the build
property we're going to add some context
uh and the context is essentially what
file we're we're building off of and so
we're going to say ltor script inside of
the root folder so uh it's going to be
here and it's going to be root in
reference to where the docker file is
and we're just going to say Docker file
but I'm going to Capital I the D here um
cuz that's what I'm going to do when we
create it now the command we're going to
run I think that's changed it the
command we're going to run and we're
going to put this in early brackets
we're going to say python since this is
a python file and then
eltor
script same thing with the networks so
we're going to say networks and then _
Network there now this is going to be
one thing that we learned in Docker so
the depends on property here is that
this container depends on other
containers and so if it has any
dependencies this container won't
initialize until the other containers it
depends on are finished building and so
if I say this depends on both the source
as well as the
destination services this script will
not run until these two are finished
initializing in which it does take time
which would make sense right because we
need to initialize the destination
database because there is no way for us
to move data if there is no data in here
yet and this isn't even ready we don't
want the script to run or else we're
going to run into a lot of errors here
so this is exactly why I wanted to use a
Docker container for the elt script so
that way we can control the way that it
functions so now that we have this going
on we're going to create a new file here
we're going to say Docker file just like
we said and now within the docker file
this is where we're going to specify a
couple things so obviously the structure
is going to look a little different here
but from is going to be the actual image
we want to use so we're going to say 3.8
h
slim is going to be the first one that
we're going to use here now what we want
to do is we want to install postest with
some command line tools so we're going
to say run um and apt get since it's
running off of Linux apt get update and
and apt get install y
postgress so that's going to install the
postgress client there we're also going
to copy so we're going to copy the
contents of the actual elt script so
that the docker container has access to
it and so we're going to say elt or
script.py this so make sure you have
that period at the end and then the
command we're going to run is again
python
_ so that is going to be the structure
here now the next thing we're going to
do is actually create our source
destination and initialize it with some
data so let's go ahead and do that so if
you go over to the repo of the custom
elt project you're going to see this
folder called sourcecore
dbor nit now now what this is primarily
holding is a SQL file that contains all
fake data so we're going to create a
couple tables and then insert values
into them so that's exactly what we're
going to go do so let me go back and
switch I'm going to create a new folder
and we're going to name it Source dbor
init as we just saw inside of there I'm
going to do init SQL and if you remember
it's exactly what we did here so we're
pointing that exact file over into this
directory of the container so that we
have access to it we're creating a a
mapping of this over into the docker
container so that way we can actually
run the commands to initialize the
source database from there now inside of
this what we're going to do is just go
in here and copy I believe I can just
copy everything here and paste it so
that's exactly what you're going to do
just make sure you have access to this
copy everything that you see inside the
folder so we can save some time going to
create a couple tables and insert some
fake data for us like I mentioned we're
going to save that and now we can
actually go about running this and and
creating everything so the way to do
that is going to be inside of our elt
script so let's fill out elt script now
all right so we are in our elt script
here and there's a couple things that
we're going to import so we're going to
import the subprocess first so this is
how we're allowing to control inputs and
outputs and things like that we're also
going to import time um this is going to
be make sense a little bit later but the
first thing we want to do is obviously
double check and I know that the docker
composed file checks to make sure that
the elt script will not run un unless
the source and the destination database
are working but we can also run a
fallback just in case so we're going to
create this function here called weight
_ 4ore postgress and uh some of the
variables we need are going to be the
host we're going to need the maxcore
retries the default value here is going
to be five delay in seconds we're going
to leave at five so after that what goes
inside this function uh we're going to
say
retries is zero while retries is less
than Max retries
we are going to say try results equals
subprocess run and then in here we're
going to say
PG is ready this say hyphen H going to
post here check equals true now this is
all going to be correlated to postest
directly capture output true and then
the text is true there a couple checks
here right I think I forgot something
here move this over and then we're also
going to put an if condition here if
accepting connections so obviously we're
pinging the actual database itself to
make sure that it's ready to go or if it
is accepting connections we're going to
say print successfully uh connected to
postest and then we're also going to
return true here and accept subprocess
do called process error as e we're going
to say print
and F error connecting to post address
colon here I'm going to use that F here
or sorry e for the error oh this to be
inside
retries if it errors we're going to add
one to the retry plus equals 1 also
going to add another print statement
here and we're going to say f retrying
in play seconds
attempt rri this is all just for logging
here and then Mac r
eyes here see where this isue here
outside of the print we're going to say
time do sleep delay seconds and then
outside of the accept print Max retries
reached exiting in case all else fails
and then we're going to return false
Okay cool so that is going to be our
check function here so I know that was a
lot but we tries spelled that wrong both
times all good okay that fix it well now
we don't have any weird Squigly now
we're going to get into actually
building out the initialization of the
source database and then moving on to
the destination well we can also add
this so we're going to say if not wait
uh underscore 4ore postgress post equals
sourcecore postgress then we're going to
say exit with the eror with code one
print um starting elt script well now we
can actually do this so uh we're going
to say sourcecore config
open this object here and so the first
thing we need to specify is going to be
the DB name and we're going to be using
dump files here if you're familiar with
postgress we can use dump files to
initialize the actual database but also
use those and dump files into the
destination so that's exactly how we're
going to be using this batch script here
for our elt and so we're going to say uh
Source DB is going to be the name of our
DB name it's actually not a uh sign it's
going to be that and then uh let me add
our here same thing here so we're going
to say user is going to be what we
specified so these are all information
that we had in the docker compos file
this is going to be the password um and
then the password was secret now for
this next one we're going to say host
now the host should be the name of the
service uh that we put inside of the
dock compost file so we're going to say
sourcecore poost that is going to be the
source config now we're going to do the
exact same thing for the destination
config DB name is
destination DB username is if I can type
properly post address password is going
to secret as well and then the host is
going to destination underscore this
destination yep no typos there perfect
now we need to create the dump command
for initializing The Source data so
underneath here we're going to say dump
uncore command we're going to say PG
uncore dump which is the command here
that we're going to use um the H flag
hyphen H we'll use the sourcecore config
and we're going to point to the host
since that's our host um let me make
sure that this has a comma for the user
so we're going to say hyphen you we're
going to say Source config and we're
going to point it to user so you can see
kind of what we're mapping each
individual flag so the host user
password all that stuff too so we're
going to also do hyphen D for the
database name and we're going to point
point to sourcecore config Dame hyphen f
is going to be the file that we're going
to use and where we're pointing that is
going to be data uncore dump needs to be
single quotes
dataor
dump. if we add this flag high and W it
will not prompt us for the password
which we don't have to do every single
time which is nice so the other thing
too is we're going to set the
environment variable to avoid the
password dump so we're going to say
subprocessor EnV equals di uh PG
password equals sourcecore config
password so now we we've created a
password RPG password environment
variable that will not ask us for the
password every single time now we're
going to execute this dump command so
we're going to say subprocess dot run
dump command which is the one we just
created point it to the environment
variable that we just created so
subprocessor EnV and then check equals
true so that's going to dump everything
into the source database now we actually
need to get everything from the source
database over to the destination so
we're going to create a load command and
it's going to look pretty much identical
to this so what I'm going to do is copy
and paste everything here but we're
going to make some slight modifications
so instead of PG dump we're going to say
psql so we're actually going to get into
the SQL command line tool we're going to
point it to the host but instead of
source it needs to be destination the
user is also the same so we need to
point it to the destination database
name is going to be the
[Music]
same now we need to or well we don't
need this since we're not pointing it to
a file well we do what we're actually
going to do is concatenate this so we're
going to put two commands here we're
going to do hyphen a comma F we're going
to delete the W uh and then we're still
pointing it to the data. dump. SQL file
now we're going to do the same
environment variable with
subprocessor EnV
equals we're actually copy and paste
this over again cuz I mean it's
literally the exact same thing except
we're going to be using the destination
here destination config now we need to
execute the load command um so what
we're going to do is we're going to say
subprocess do run load command EnV is
going to equal subprocessor EnV and then
we're going to do the check equals true
again and we're going to print just for
our own purposes ending elt script cool
so now this is going to be our full on
elt script now how do we run this well
what we're going to do is use Docker to
completely run everything here so let's
go ahead and take a look at what that
looks like because we've made everything
and hooked everything up with Docker
compos it's going to be a simple as this
all we have to do inside of our terminal
obviously make sure that we're in the
directory that we created I'm going to
run Docker compose up uh I forgot to do
this so I forgot to change the host to
postgress here um let me make sure
that's that okay so I had a slight error
but all we have to do is we're going to
do Docker compose up what Docker compose
all services. Source oh does it not need
this uh I might have screwed up here
again which is fine we all make mistakes
so it doesn't actually need this
section here uh let's see if that will
fix it we're going to leave this in here
all we're running into a couple things
here so _ script so let's do let's just
debug this live cuz why not/ scripts so
this should just be elt I pretty sure
there you go okay so just a couple
errors here but hey nothing that's going
to shake us up but so now that we've run
Docker compose up we're actually going
to go through and build out the images
so we're pulling down from the docker
compos or from Docker Hub to to uh build
out these images so now what we can see
is we might be running into something
here but as you can see in the logs and
let me pull this over so you can
actually see it so through the logs what
we've done is we have we've initialized
the destination database and the source
database which is good and then we've
also created the database we've inserted
a couple tables and then the values for
them but it looks like we ran into an
issue with the elt script uh starting
elt script so it looks like that was
good Trace back on line
[Music]
uh okay so let's look at our PG script
so you can kind of see like all the
little nuances here with creating a
batch script and like this is on purpose
uh I I wanted to make sure that we ran
into some issues here I mean obviously I
would like to not run into issues but
comes with coding comes with building
out these things manually uh and we'll
see that it gets a little bit easier to
deal with later down the line
um so on line 54 is when it said that we
had a bug here so subprocess run dump
command I think this should be a i u or
capital u here go ahead and try this one
more time so what we're going to do is
Docker compose
down type oh my God okay so the source
is ready to connect still running into
an issue here um on the subprocess still
on line
54 so we've started the elt script
return nonzero exit status let's try
without the chck back here that's not it
DB name sourcecore DB post you got
secret Source postgress
destination for postgress okay so I've
deleted the image on Docker let's try
running this one more time let's build
the image again and see if it fixes it e
error oh I see the issue okay so I screw
that up I think that should be good now
so let's Docker comos down again dock ER
compose up just a casual typo error here
I believe it's still not going to work
here cuz I think it's still read the old
one so what I'm going to do is kill this
Docker compose up or sorry Docker
compose down rid of these now let's go
into Docker and you can see kind of like
what the troubleshooting so we built
this image and I don't think it's
changed it so I'm going to delete that
um we're going to go back into the
terminal here say Docker compos up so
we're going to re build the image and it
should there we go okay so now you can
see after some troubleshooting and then
some small typos here and there uh we
have
successfully gotten our logs back and
then at the end we had our ending elt
script so the way to check our work now
is if we open a new terminal let me make
this a little bit bigger let go back
into our other directory so CDT I'm
going to say Docker exact and this is
from what we learned in the other
tutorial on Docker so Docker exact and
we're going to use the interactive flag
here uh we're going to grab the name of
our _ script one so I believe the full
name of it should be this so we're going
to grab I'm sorry we're not grabbing
this we want to grab the destination
name so we're going to grab _ postgress
one so that's going to be the name then
we're going to say psql we want to run
the command line the postgress command
line hyphen you with the user postgress
now if I hit enter we're going to be in
here the one thing we do need to do is
we're going to say/ C for connect do the
destination DB so now we can see that we
are in the destination database now if I
do slash this is back slash by the way
or forward forward slash I think uh is/
DT you can see that all of the tables
are now inside of the destination
database now if I do select all from
actors now I need to add the semicolon
you can see that all the data that we
inserted into the Source database is now
into the destination database this is
now fully working it is not automated at
all but you can see that our bat script
is now successfully working just by
simply taking the dump commands that are
built into postgress and then moving
those in to the destination database now
this is postest to postest so this is
very very simple but you can see that
even this is a very basic script but
there's a lot of moving Parts when it
comes to building out a script manually
and so when things change or if you're
trying to connect postgress over into
let's say another database type where
you potentially have to match schema and
things like that in this case we didn't
have to worry about that because the
same database same protocol and
everything but if we're working with
something else it can get very very
tricky so that's why we're going to be
implementing a lot more open source
tooling but for this next part we're
actually going to add a Cron job to this
to automate the script a little bit
because as of right now we are simply
just manually triggering this so if we
we needed to do this every day every 3
days we could actually add that in here
so let's go ahead and do that now okay
so actually iine the next evolution is
not going to be the KRON job next it's
actually going to be DBT DBT is going to
be an open source tool that we can
utilize here in order to write custom
Transformations or custom models on top
of the data that we've just sent into
the destination database so you can take
for example that we had a use case where
this destination database is primarily
going to be used by data analysts or
some sort of data scientists and they
need their data formatted or structured
in a certain way where we're combining
certain tables together they can't write
SQL or something like that and they
actually just need it a certain way or
something along those lines we can use
DBT to have those custom models so that
by the time the data is inside the
destination we can run DBT on top of
that data and then write custom models
here creating custom tables and things
like that and it allows us to have
certain capabilities it also allows us
to even write python to run SQL scripts
and things like that so let's go ahead
and see what that looks like and
implement it now there are a couple
prerequisites you need in order to run
DBT successfully on your machine or even
using Docker so let's go ahead and take
a look at what that looks like and
actually get it installed all right so
I'm here on the DPT docs which we will
also list down in the description just
so you can get to it pretty easily now
there is some things you need to do
locally uh not everything you can do
here through docker so the first thing
you need to do is obviously I'm on a Mac
so most of the instructions here are
going to be from Mac but you do need to
have this installed locally and the way
to do that is if you probably have Pip
if you have python installed and so
you're going to follow all these
instructions I think you could pretty
much skip these ones right here uh
you're going to want to follow this one
for sure I think actually you can
probably skip that one too the main one
here is installing the actual adap
you're not just installing the adapter
but you're also installing DBT core
which is the open source version of DBT
now I've already done this but if you
run DBT install DBT hyphen postest we're
installing the adapter of postgress that
utilizes DBT as well as DBT core you're
going to go ahead and run that locally
I've already done that uh as you could
see here so if I say uh DBT hyen hyen
version you can see that it's going to
list pretty much I have 1.62 installed
I'm not going to update for the sake of
this tutorial but there's 1.66 and I
have the postest version installed as
well so make sure you through this
installation really quickly and that way
we can actually go through and create
our models so make sure you do that that
is just the only prerequisite for this
section okay so now that we have DBT
installed let me go ahead and show you
how we can initialize a project here so
it's as simple as DBT innit we're going
to run DBT in nit inside of the root
directory excuse me uh now it's going to
ask us for the name of our project we're
going to say uh custom I don't know
custom postgress so it's going to say
custom _ postgress and you can see it's
creating these folders here for us now
we have the database we would like to
use it's asking us right here for
postgress and obviously it's the only
adapter that we installed so we're going
to hit number one and therefore it's
created us our it's created two folders
actually if we take a look on the right
left hand side it's created logs for us
so we now have logs for anything
regarding DBT as well as our project for
DBT so it has a couple folders here
analysis macros models seeds snap shots
and tests primarily what we're going to
be focusing on is the models and macros
for now uh and then the the rest of it
is is kind of like you know you can
learn as you go but for the sake of this
tutorial we're going to be focusing on
these folders here so there are other
couple things that we need to do in
order to set up the project itself
before we actually write our models the
one thing we actually have to do is
going to be this so I've just copied and
pasted this one command but you're going
to do Nano and inside of the complete
root of your local machine when you
install DBT using pip it actually
creates this DBT directory and inside
that folder is a profiles. yl file so
what we're going to do is go in there
and you can see that I've already set
this up but inside of the dev profile it
does say post Crestor Transformations
I'm going to go ahead and change this
because this is now different so what
I've done now is I'm going to do change
the name of this because it's no longer
post Transformations that's what I
normally did uh this is going to be
custom postgress you can see it's done
that down here it it is actually done
that down here here actually you know
what I'm probably just going to do that
instead I'm going to
post so now that we're inside of this
folder you can see that I've already
done this prior but if we were to go
down here into the custom post crust
profile which is created for me because
of this new project you can see here
there there's two different outputs
there's prod and Dev we're going to be
primarily focusing on dev and we do need
to fill out the actual information here
so inside of host I'm actually to do
host. doer. internal which is needed in
order for DBT to actually recognize the
docker containers that we were trying to
access here which is going to be our
destination database so make sure that
this says host. doer. internal and it'll
read the actual Network or IP address of
your Docker container for the
destination database for the port here
this is going to be 5434 I'm pretty sure
for the destination for the user we're
going to change this over to postest for
the password
we're going to change this over to
secret DB name will be
destination DB and then I forget what I
actually put for the schema here uh
schema should be public and then I
forgot to fill up the threads here so
let's change this to one all right so
and the target here is going to be Dev
so obviously make sure that says it by
default it should just Target the dev
profile but now that we have our
information filled out here it should
have the correct information to connect
to our destination database I believe if
I do write out maybe not write out but
if we say x save modified we're going to
hit yes tab to complete and hit enter
okay so this should have saved it now
the other thing to do here is inside of
the DBT project. file the one thing to
note is that obviously the profile we
just wrote is the custom _ postgress you
don't have to change anything here
except for this bottom section inside of
the bottom section is going to be how
we're forming our models now inside of
the models folder you can see that
there's an example folder and then a
couple of models here what we're
actually going to do is we're going to
change this there's a couple options
inside the material section but because
we're using postest tables we actually
want to change this to table if you keep
it as view we're actually not going to
see any of the tables that we created
come through or anything like that or
DBT is not going to be able to recognize
it so we have to change it to a table
now that we've done that we can actually
go in and write our models so let's go
ahead and do that all right so we are
inside of the models folder here and
inside of this example folder are some
custom examples that they have created
for us uh we don't really need to see
this because we're going to be writing
our own so I'm actually going to go
ahead and delete both of these we're
going to keep the schema. yaml for now
well we're going to reference that later
but let's create our models here so you
can think of models as just SQL files
we're just querying the data but we're
morphing the data around to the needs
that we need so we just do it once here
and then once the destination database
has its data everything that we've
queried here all the modifications and
the new tables that we've created will
end up inside of the destination
database and you'll see what I mean by
all that once we have it all hooked up
the first thing we need to do is
actually Source the data itself because
it can't just simply reference tables
inside of a destination database without
having the actual reference itself so
what we're going to do is we're going to
create our first one so we're going to
say film _ actors which is a table that
we're actually writing over into the
destination database and this is simply
just creating a reference for us to
create the custom models so this isn't
necessarily a custom model here um so
we're going to write some some SQL here
select all from and then we're going to
do double curly brackets here and inside
of that we're going to say the source of
our data is going to come from
destination database and the name it for
this that we're going to reference it
from is going to be Filmore actors we're
going to need to wrap both of these in
single quotes very cool now what we've
done is we've sourced the destination
database and we've taken the film actors
table and now we have a film actors's
reference let me go ahead and copy and
paste this we're going to do that again
for the actors table so actors. SQL
we're going to paste this in here and
we're simply going to change this over
to actors and we're going to do the same
for films films. SQL so we have our
references now we can actually create
our custom models but again before we do
that we have to have some prerequisite
work so for the schemas these are our
custom models here our our DBT models
and we do have to specify what the
schema of these are going to be so that
if we do need to test anything which you
should be testing you can run a model or
you can run DBT against all of these SQL
files and if it doesn't match what we've
specified inside the schema we're going
to get thrown back errors so you should
definitely always do this what I'm going
to do is I'm going to head over into our
file here and I'm going to look into the
models and example fold and we're going
to have a couple things so schema. AML
is what we want we see that there's a
films table here and every bit of schema
here for that one the actors film actors
film ratings I think I need the film
ratings one two as a yeah that's fine so
what we're going to actually just do
here is copy and paste this whole thing
I implore you to do that too we're going
to paste that in there and now we have
the schema for all the tables that we
just add now the other thing too that we
need to do is we're going to go ahead
and copy over the sources EML so now
we're specifying the raw data from the
destination database so I'm going to
copy this as well and you can see film
actor and film actors literally the
exact tables that we just copied so
we're going to go in here and create a
new file called sources. EML and paste
everything that we just saw so now we
actually have sources that we can point
to regarding these files or tables
essentially that we're querying from so
you can see if we think about this from
the top down data is theoretic Ally
already written inside of the
destination database DBT is going to run
after we've moved data over so the data
is already there and from there what
we're doing is taking in the data so
that way we can modify it and create a
custom model with that data so all we're
doing here is referencing data that we
already have now let's go in and create
the custom models to formulate and
modify the data we have into a table
that we want okay so the first model we
going to create inside of the example
folder I'm going to name Filmore
ratings. SQL so what we're going to be
doing is appending the films as well as
the actors together to create one table
but it's going to be primarily focused
on the film ratings so let's get to it
all right so what we're going to do
inside of this file is we're actually
going to create two different tables and
then use a join to create one if that
makes sense so the first one we're going
to call is with filmscore with ratings
as and then this is where we're going to
run our sequel to create this table so
we're going to say select
filmcore ID
title release _ date make sure you're
adding commas price rating these are all
from the table that we already have this
is going to be user rating this is where
we add something very specific so this
is going to be a case so what the case
is kind of like you can think of an if
state statement per se so we're going to
say when user rating is greater than or
equals to uh let's say
4.5 then we want the rating to say
excellent uh we're going to add another
one where user rating is going to be
greater than or equals to 4.0 so kind of
like in the in between there and we're
going to say that we want the rating to
read good and then the last one we're
going to do is going to the user rating
is going to be greater than or equals to
3.0 then we're we're going to say that
this is going to be average else we're
going to label it as poor and we're
going to end as rating uncore
category so that ends this case
statement here and this is where the
reference comes in so we're going to say
from and we're going to open the double
curly brackets again and if we say ref
parentheses films we're going to be
pulling from this here because we
labeled it as films so now we can
actually reference it here within
this little query here one thing I
forgot to mention for this specifically
is you saw that we say with and as or
with films with ratings this is actually
what's referred to as a CTE or comment
table expression so you can see this as
a wrapper of this query kind of like a
subquery per se but it makes it easy to
write queries that are maintainable and
they're also scoped just to this CTE so
it will not like go outside of this so
this allows us to write subqueries and
then ultimately reference them later
inside of this file so it is actually
really really nice part of DBT that lets
us write CTE uh to kind of formulate
these custom models so that's just
something I forgot to mention when we
were first writing this but remember
this is a CTE or Common Table expression
all right so now that we have our first
CTE so let's write the second one I
added a comma after the CTE so that way
we can string on another one this one is
going to be films with underscore with
uncore actors as and then that's going
to open our CTE here our second one so
we're going to say select and we're
going to do the Alias here um f.
Filmore ID f. tile and then we're going
to do a string aggregator or string
aggregation with a.
actor undor name we're going to pend it
with a comma there and we're going to do
as actors so we're aggregating actor
names for each film here and and then
we're also going to hit the reference so
from double curly brackets reference
films and then obviously we're going to
enable the Alias here with f my auto
completes that but there we go so then
we're also going to left join Filmore
actors table and we're going to give
that fa for film actors on f. Filmore ID
if it equals the film actors. film idect
uh we're going to do another left join
here referencing the this left join we
need to this so let's go ahead and do
that so forgot the curly brackets or I'm
sorry the uh parenthesis and single
quotes there um let's add the actors for
this reference obviously this one is
going to be a on fa. actor _ ID if it
equals the a. actor ID and then we're
going to group by the f. Filmore ID and
the f. tile okay so that's going to be
the second CTE so we have two now
technically two series films with
ratings and the films with actors so
we've taken the film ID and the title
and we've joined the two tables that we
had here we have the film actors and the
actors table so these are obviously you
know we worked with these before but the
film actors and the actors is the bridge
to the films table so now we can
actually join them to create one so now
we're going to have the main query here
we're going to select fwf do asterisk
here and we're going to say fwa film
with actors. actors the filmscore with
now you can see underscore ratings you
can see how we're referencing the actual
CTE now and then we're going to label
this as fwf for the Alias then we're
going to say left join films with actors
which we're going to label fwa on
fwf do Filmore ID if it equals the film
with actors do
Filmore now we're creating essentially
what could be two tables two tables
using the references we've created and
now we're actually joining them together
using this custom model now if we were
to want to run this we now need to set
up the dock container for DBT so let's
go ahead and do that and then run this
custom model just to see what it would
look like okay so we are back inside of
our Docker compos file let's go ahead
and add the DBT service so underneath
the elt script I'm going to say DBT
which is going to be the name of our
service the image I want to use is going
to be
gc. i/ DBT laabs SL DBT postgress and
then the version is
1.47 uh this as of right now at the time
of this recording is most likely out of
date but it's just what I use so I'm
going to go ahead and run with it the
command I'm going to run here uh I'm
actually going to run a couple now I'm
going to open this square brackets and
the first one I'm going to do is run so
this is technically DBT run DBT run is
the command you would use
in order to run your models on top of
the destination so I'm going to string a
couple here so we're going to say run
and then we're actually going to do
we're going to point to the profiles
directory so if I do double hyphen
profiles hypher not period I need a
comma we're going to say that is going
to be in the uh root here and then if
we're going to point to the project
directory then we're going to point to/
DB T which is the name essentially going
to be the name of our project directory
here the one thing I also want to do uh
well we can leave this out for now
actually um so after that we're going to
do networks and this will be altore
Network so we can keep it on the same
network here and now we're going to
point some volumes here so with the
volumes we have the actual project
itself so you notice I said SL DBT so
here we're actually going to create
another mapping to point to DBT because
if we remember correctly on Docker
containers every directory here is
pretty much going to be pointing to the
directory inside of the actual Docker
container and not your local machine so
you have to map the docker container to
look at where the actual project is
going to be on your local machine so
we're going to create that mapping and
this is going to be/ custom postgress
and then uh from there we're going to do
the colon to create the mapping to The
Container path and then the container
path is simply just going to be/ DBT
which we've pointed right here now we
need to create another volume here uh
let me add a space here because that
requires a space uh we're going to point
to the um the DBT profile that we did so
we're going to need the squiggly Tilda
we need squiggly SL DBT and we're going
to point this over into the root which
is where we pointed if I could spell
normally uh this is where the profiles
directory was which is going to be in/
root so now we're mapping our local DBT
folder with the profiles. emo file to
the/ root of the docker container
hopefully that makes a bunch of sense
cuz in my mind it kind of does so we're
also going to say depends on the elt
undersource scripts we want DBT only to
run because remember when this container
starts we're running this command and if
we run DBT run on top of the destination
database without it having any data this
will not work because there nothing to
reference and it has nothing to write
data on so we need this to make sure
that it depends on the elt script and
the elt script depends on the two
databases so this is working down the
line we've essentially created a uh work
line here and then for the environments
we need two here so we need DBT profile
this one is going to be it's going to be
default and then we have another one
this one doesn't need a hyphen actually
cuz we made that mistake last time and
then we need DBT uncore Target and this
one is going to be Dev so this is going
to be everything we need for the DBT
container now all we need to do go ahead
and clear this I don't think compos down
Docker compos down everything uh I think
the volumes are still up but that's
totally fine so now we're going to do
Docker compose up did I type that
correctly
hc. i/
DBT lab
slbt post press s oh uh 1.7 okay that's
another one another typo there we go so
we're going to go ahead and let that run
here so elt script exited Code Zero so
that's a good sign now the DBT one
should pop up invalid not a project
missing DBT unor pro. file okay so
invalid project directory project
directory here custom _ post press maybe
we do not need this let's go ahead and
clear this let's do Docker down SLB and
then so maybe custom oh I'm dumb
uh it should have been an underscore you
can see all the typos and everything
really does make a difference here so
let's run that again and that should map
to the correct project now hopefully
there we go so it's ran successfully I
think unable to do partial parsing
encoun an error error sources. yo
runtime error sources. Yeo list of
actors film actors ra eror while parsing
of block mapping uni code okay so there
was an error in our sources file here
somewhere that might have been it um 13
and 14 Filmore actors okay let's do this
one more time I think my cat may have
done something with that so you can see
there a lot of back and forth here
scripts ran successfully okay it's
taking a little bit longer which is
totally fine here model fims was which
was not F there's a lot of typas going
on film ratings so if we go into Filmore
ratings reference films fil
okay here's the typo let's Docker
compose down again so also uh if you're
curious if I'm Docker composing down
hyphen V I'm actually killing the
volumes every single time just to make
sure that everything is working even if
we're starting straight from the
beginning without any data persisting so
I'm that's the only reason why I'm doing
that um so now we Docker compose up
again this should work unless I've made
even more typos okay so we're doing that
again there we go okay so now you can
see that we've successfully run our
models so we've created a couple models
here the first one was the actors the
first one was the film actors the F and
the second or the third one was the
films so these are all our references so
we've successfully taken that in but now
we've actually done the fourth one which
is the model for the Filmore ratings so
you can see that that's actually worked
now now if we were to go Docker exact
hyphen it and then I think it was elt
Destination _ postgress hyph 1 and then
we do
psql hyphen U postgress so then we go
here we do c
destination DB we connect there and then
slash DT so now you can see Filmore
ratings which is the new table that
we've written in DBT is actually written
now if we select all from Filmore
ratings and it with the semicolon you
can see that if I move this over it's a
little big but you can see that our case
has gone in here uh it's kind of cut off
just because of the way that my terminal
looks you can see everything is in there
so we have our actors we have our film
ID we have the release date the price
but the most important part is the
rating that we've created here so the
case statement worked successfully so
anything above a 4.5 was excellent
anything below that between 4.0 and 4.4
was good and you had no average one so
you can see that we've actually created
this custom model successfully uh along
with the actor and the actor name so you
had Inception with Leonardo DiCaprio it
just looks a little weird because of the
way that um if I were to do this here so
let's do the same one so now you can see
it it it looks a well it still looks a
little weird but anyways you can see
that it works so that is creating a
simple model in DBT now let's look at
some other Advanced options you can do
inside of DBT to make your queries a
little bit more Dynamic is the best way
to put it okay so now that we've
actually created the models I told you
that we're going to get into some
advanced stuff with DBT and that's why I
mentioned the macros folder so you can
think of macros as sort of like a
reusable components of DBT where you may
have some sort of queries that you want
to reuse and is universal through pretty
much all your models so what if you
could just create a macro where you
didn't have to rewrite the same thing
every single time well you can
absolutely do that with macros let's
take the Filmore ratings file for
example say we wanted to generate this
every single time uh now that's probably
not going to happen but let's say we
wanted to do it and so let's just go
ahead and actually take the whole file
and cut it now inside of the macros
folder what we're going to create is
we're going to say Filmore ratings macro
do SQL file everything's going to be a
SQL file here now what we're going to do
is we're going to start the file with
curly brackets both sides are going to
have a parenthesis so double parentheses
and inside that we're going to say macro
generate uncore Filmore ratings uh and
then we're going to parenthesis after
now the end of the macro is also going
to have curly brackets is also going to
have double parentheses but inside the
parentheses or I'm sorry inside of the
uh percent signs you're going to say n
macro in one word now in between that is
where your macro is going to go so I'm
going to go ahead and paste what we just
took from film ratings into the macro
now Filmore ratings has nothing but if
we were to go inside of film ratings now
all we have to say is two early brackets
and we're going to call the generate
Filmore ratings macro so you can see
that this is the model that we're
actually writing and the macros never
actually gets written but if I were
going to go back into our terminal here
and let's close this and let's say
dockor compos down hph V so let's kill
the volumes here we're going to say
Docker compose up and it's going to run
through everything all over again so
let's go ahead and let that go through
through really quickly DBT is going to
start running and then you can see we
still have four models being written if
we go back now over to the destination
database uh SLC
destination DP and then /dt the Filmore
ratings table is still getting written
and if I do select all from
Filmore ratings you can see that we're
still writing exactly what we wrote inil
underscore ratings but we've only been
using the macro so you can see that
literally anything inside of the macro
file in between this section here and
here is going to be written exactly as
shown so if I were to say let's I don't
know let's create a a macro for this
case which probably is more plausible
than anything so if I wanted to say
generate
ratings macro do SQL and we wanted to do
the same thing where we go uh let's just
percent sign this generates ratings and
then we're going to end macro right and
then we paste this inside all we have to
do now is then just say generate ratings
call that and then we should be able to
do the same thing uh if we do this
Docker compos down be compose up let
that run again yes it takes a little bit
of time to run it every single time but
you know this is just what what it comes
with it be much harder is undefined
under undefined generate uncore ratings
it's not generate uncore ratings uh it's
generate underscore rating wondering if
you can't call CT EAS here so now you
can see kind of how macros could work is
it it allows you to have reusable
queries throughout your whole DBT
project essentially to just plug and
play in and not have to rewrite the same
thing every single time so if you have
reusable queries that you can use go
ahead head and use macros because it's
very very efficient in terms of not
having to you know it it implores the
dry method of software engineering where
you know don't repeat yourself you don't
have to repeat yourself every single
time if you have the same queries over
and over and over again so utilize
macros when you can now let's move over
into gingas which is another feature of
DBT okay so this next section that I
just mentioned with gingas gingas are
essentially what allow you to create
conditionals or add control structures
to your SQL queries so for example that
we're going to use is let's say we
wanted to select a specific title but
using a Ginga so we didn't have to
actually put it within our actual SQL
query that's what it allows us to do it
could allow you to select you know do we
want to use the prod Target instead of
the dev Target inside of our DBT project
then we could do that as well and we can
change the way that queries are done
again adding a control structure so
let's go ahead and inside of our example
folder we're going to create a file
called specific under _ movie SQL and
inside of that is where we're going to
start with our Ginger here so again
starts with a curly bracket and then two
percent signs and inside of that we're
going to say sets so when you see sets
is essentially what is starting our
control structure here and we're going
to set Filmore title to equal for this
example we're going to say Dunkirk cuz I
know that's going to be a movie inside
of the demo or the um test database here
so Dunkirk is going to be a movie that
we're going to look for right now inside
of that we're going to say select so
this is the actual query itself select
all from and we're going to reference
the uh films table here where let's
practice here where title equals and
then we can say in the single quotes
Filmore title so that is obviously the
variable that we've set up here right
that's going to be our Ginger here we're
setting a control structure where we
only want to select the title where
dynamically the value we've set here is
dunker and obviously this can be
anything we want it to be but so let's
go ahead and save that and then run our
docker compose up here and let
everything go when DBT runs we should
have a fifth model that runs which is
going to be our specific movie and so
let's go ahead and let that run here
there's going to be the fifth it's all
pass very good let's run our destination
database and SLC into it so
destination
db/dt and you can see specific movie is
now a table inside of this database and
so if I say select all from specific
uncore movie you can see Dunkirk as well
as all of its information including the
film ID the release date price rating
and user rating is going to be in there
because we've used the ginger in there
now it allows you to to pretty much do
anything you want you know if we wanted
to go into the macro here and create
conditionals where we have an excellent
condition a good condition or an average
condition and we set those to be this
number we can absolutely do that and
allows us to do that outside of the
query so that way we can know that up
here we can set it to a different movie
you know if we wanted to do Inception we
we're only changing it Inception pretty
sure that's how you spell it if it's not
that's going to be very awkward but so
let's do this Docker compose down V
Docker compose up let's run this again
and so when we run this we should see
that the specific movie has then changed
over to Inception instead of dunker
therefore showing that the ginger works
and it it allows for a little bit more
readability right because you can see
that our film title we've set it to a
variable we're not you know manually
searching for a a movie here and we're
going to do select all from a specific
movie and now you can see Inception is
now there so again a very simple example
of what a ginger is and kind of how it
works but go ahead and play with it I
implore you to kind of you know
integrate gingas with macros to really
really you know use the full power of
macros and gingas together and I think
it could really 10x your SQL queries and
your custom models from within DBT and
really just Excel that process of the
whole data engineering SL data analytics
process all together okay so as I've
mentioned before we're going to be
adding a Cron job to this not ideal I
guess you could say in the sense of that
like it's not necessarily the best
implementation I guess you could say but
there are a lot of other people out
there that use Crown jobs I'm going to
show you the way you can Implement a
crown job because again you don't want
to manually be triggering these data
syns or this pipeline to be running on
your own you kind of want some
automation here so the first thing we're
going to do is add the crown job I'll
show you how you can do that in this
type of implementation obviously there's
different ways to implement it but this
will eventually evolve into US adding a
tool called airflow air flow is going to
be an orchestration tool that easily
allow us to kind of have more control
than a Cron job over each individual
task inside of our project to allow us
to schedule it properly I think the best
thing that you can have is more control
outside of just scheduling when it runs
and so let me go ahead and show you how
the Cron job works first and then we'll
move into airflow and other
orchestration tools like that okay so
for the Cron job the main file we got to
go into is going to be the docker file
now because we're primarily main working
on the El script and we want to schedule
that this is where we're going to run
everything so just going to be some
slight modifications here so the one
thing we're going to do is we're going
to add KRON to the end of the list of
installs we're going to do so we're
going to run for postgress client as
well as cron underneath here now what
we're going to do is we're going to
create a new file called
start.sh now this is going to be a bash
script that we run so this sits in the
root directory and we'll modify this
later but above this copy script or
above this copy command that we have
we're going to add another one and this
one's going to be start.sh uh and we're
going to copy this over to the app
directory of Docker so that Docker now
has the start.sh file within its own
container here the working directory is
going to be the app so we're going to
say worker is going to be slapp here in
between work directory and command this
is where we're going to add the Cron job
now for this example we're going to run
the script let's say every day at 3:00
a.m. so we're going to do a run command
here and then we're going to Echo and
then in quotes we're going to say zero
space three and then three asterisks and
I'm sure there's like you know sources
online that can show you kind of like
how to properly write a Cron job for a
specific time this is just the one that
I have now we're going to say python SLA
_
script.py and then outside of that we're
going to do the divider here and then
we're going to say cron tab now we're
going to save this and then if we go
back into start. s this is where we're
going to write the uh how to actually
start the Cron demon so at the very top
we're going to say cron and and that
pretty much is what's going to run the
cron and have it run in the background
and then python slapp
_ script.py what this is going to do is
we have the bash script and it's in our
working directory we're going to run
this command here when the docker
container starts and now this bash
script is going to run the pron Damon in
the background and then run this every
single time it's 3:00 a.m. and so we'll
run the bat script at 3:00 a.m. every
single time due to this Crown so again a
very simple implementation of how the
cron is supposed to work obviously it's
hard to demonstrate this because it's
6:50 p.m. right now so I can't really
just wait here until 3:00 a.m. but now
at 3:00 a.m. every single time this will
run so yeah that's essentially how this
Cron job is going to work now let's move
into how airflow is going to play in the
mix and how we can now orchestrate this
using a real open source tool that's out
there in the wild all right so in this
section we're going to be adding airflow
to our project and as I mentioned before
airflow is an orchestration tool open
source that allows you to essentially
have a top down view of every single
task and say Hey I want my elt script to
run first and then once this finishes
and is
successful and that's exactly what we're
going to do here we're going to
orchestrate all of our tools and all of
the working pieces that we have right
now to make sure that they work
sequentially here and you know there's a
lot of different use cases with airflow
or other open source tools like Daxter
or prefect but we're simply going to be
using airflow as our orchestration tool
to make sure that our pipeline is
working the way we want it to and has
some form of automation here all right
so first thing we're going to do is
going to create a new folder here and
we're going to name this airflow and
inside of airflow we're going to have
another folder called dags and a dag is
simply a directed acyclic graph I think
is how you pronounce the a part but so
the dag is what we write in order to
orchestrate all of our tasks together
and also put in some of our Logic for
each task so that's what we're going to
be writing here in DBT we were writing
uh models custom models in airflow we
write dags or in any orchestration tool
we're going to be writing a dag so that
is another term for you to put into your
brain as knowledge to know as a data
engineer the other thing we're also
going to create here is a file not
inside of the dags folder so this is
going to go into the root folder of
airflow but this is going to be airflow.
CFG I think we just need this for
airflow specifically we don't need to
put anything in it but if you needed to
do anything with your configuration of
airf flow this is going to be the file
that you're going to put it in now that
we have this structure put together
let's go ahead and go into our Docker
compos file and then add the airflow
service this is going to be a little
extensive because it is a big service so
we're going to take our time with this
one and really go through it all right
so uh underneath the DBT section we're
going to go here and add a couple spaces
because we're actually going to be
adding quite a bit of new Services here
that have to work with airf flow it
would be a lot but I've narrowed it down
to be very minimal here so we don't have
to worry about that too much so the
first thing we're actually going to add
is going to be another postgress service
and why are we adding another postgress
service here well it's because airflow
needs a database to store its metadata
and its logs so this is the database
that's going to go into it's going to be
the same look here where we're going to
say postgress and the latest image here
right um networks we're going to tie
into the elt uncore network and then for
the environment let's do this so
environment we're going to do postgress
user is going to equal airflow here we
have postgress password which is going
to equal also airflow and then for the
postgress DB this is going to be airflow
so very simple there now fix this now
that's the metadata service so you can
name that whatever you want but I'm for
Simplicity sake I'm going to keep it as
postgress next thing we need to do is
going to be anit airflow service now for
the inet airflow service what this is
primarily doing here is initializing the
user and the database that we just
created alt together for airflow so we
had we're going to add two more services
after this but this is a very important
service for us because without this
we're not going to have the admin user
and be able to create new connections
and things like that so this is very
important here now the image that we're
going to add is going to be Apache so
the Apache project open source projects
airflow and then latest this is going to
be the same for pretty much every single
uh I think it's going to be the same for
every single one but I could be wrong uh
anyway so image this is going to depend
on postgress cuz we need that database
to be initialized essentially before we
initialize airflow because without it
we're going to have some errors here
networks again we're going to say _
Network for the environments we're going
going to say this is going to be a long
one so airflow underscore underscore so
two underscores database underscore
uncore SQL underscore Alchemy _ con for
connection is going to equal and this is
going to be pointing to our postgress
data base here that we just created so
postgress
plusy cop G2 col SL SL airflow for
username and password here at postgress
SL airflow okay so that's that's a long
one but that's going to be the
environment there now last one we need
is a command the command we're going to
say uh less than or greater than sign
and in we're going to say bash I see in
quotes airfow EB and nit to initialize
the database for airflow and and string
on another one here push it over here
say airflow users create so we're this
is where we create the admin account
username airflow password is going to be
password let's just say first first name
is going to John last name is going to
be do we want the role here to be admin
and then the email we need to set let's
say admin at ample cool all right so
that's a pretty long one there already
let's go down here into the next service
that we need to create so that's our
initialization of airflow now we're
going to get into the actual like UI of
air flow which is going to be the web
server service let me add some spacing
here the image we're actually going to
create a Docker file for this so we need
to do that first now in the root of the
directory here we're going to say Docker
file and then in here we're going to say
from Apache SL airflow latest so the
same thing that we did uh with the
initialization of airf flow now we're
going to say run tip install Apache
airflow providers Docker now this is
going to come in handy later on but we
do need this in order to run this
command here airflow has a bunch of
different providers for you to access
different Integrations Docker being one
of them and there's going to be another
couple ones that we're going to use
later down the line but Docker is the
one we need so now that we have this
we're going to go back into our Docker
compos file and then for the build
section we're going to say build context
just add the dot here the docker file
we're going to point to Docker file uh
just capitalize this part the user here
is going to be root because we want the
root here here and then it depends on
the postgress service so we do not want
airfall to initialize until the metadata
store essentially is is initialized
networks we're going to point over to
the elt network and this is going to be
a special one here so extra hosts extra
hosts is going to be an interesting one
because we are running everything on
Docker we actually need this for special
reasons that'll come up later but so in
double quotes we're going to say host.
doer. internal and then we're actually
going to point that to host Gateway okay
so that points to inside Docker the host
Gateway that's going to come in handy
later so now that we have that we're
going to point to some volumes here now
the volumes are going to be very
important so we have our dags that we
need to find So within that we're going
to say/ airflow SL dags so now we have
our dags folder now we need to map it so
we're going to map it to the SL opt
slair flow/ dags so now we have the same
directory of dags inside the opt folder
and then it'll go to airflow deck so now
we have that inside of our Docker
container next one next one is going to
be the elt script that we have because
we need access to that
so/ is the folder that we have and then
we're going to say we going to map that
over again to/ opt SL airflow elt so now
we have our own elt folder with the
script and all of its contents which is
just the bash script there now we need
the Transformations because we're also
going to be orchestrating not only the
script but we're also going to be
orchestrating DBT and we need access to
those files so we're going to say slash
custom hostress that is going to map
over to slop SL DBT now we have the DBT
folder in there we're going to need the
profiles for DBT so we're going to say
Tilda sl. DBT and then we're going to
point that over to SL root
sl. I hopefully this is all making sense
here this one is going to be opening up
essentially giving airflow access to the
essentially the docker Network so we
this is going to be very important here
so we're going to say /var SL run/ doer.
sock we're giving access to the socket
there SLV bar we mapping get to SL far
SL run/ doer okay cool now for the
environment variables and this is going
to get really long here so we're going
to get environment variables here the
first one is going to be load underscore
x = n these are all just going to be
needed for airf flow executor equals
local and we're going to say airflow and
then we're mapping this back to the
database here soore undor database
Alchemy con so I've just copy and paste
this over actually cool so I've got that
now one thing airflow does need is it's
going to need a fernet key underscore
fetor key so that's only one underscore
there and then we're going to say equals
it essentially encrypts the username and
password it's for a security reason
we're just going to do that because you
know for the sake of this video so I've
actually if we go to orchestration
airflow I have this command which I will
also leave for you in the description
but this is essentially going to
generate our fernet key for us and what
we're going to do is copy and paste that
command into our terminal and it should
spit out to us a key which we will then
use and paste here so now that is our
fet key that we're going to just leave
in and will be used for encryption sake
right and for security there's that uh
now we're going to need airflow uncore
uncore web server
uncore default user underscore username
and that's just going to be airflow I'm
actually going to copy this and then
just change the last bit here to say
oops say password and this was going to
be password cool next environment
variable here we're going to go airflow
uncore un 1core www uncore user uncore
username equals airflow same thing copy
and paste this password then the last
thing we need is going to be
airflow web server underscore uncore
secretor key that's just going to be
secret cool all right last bits here
we're going to say ports so we need
expose the ports here uh this is going
to sit on port 8080 so we're going to
say 8080 here so that's how we're going
to access the web server and the command
we're going to run this web cool now now
the one thing that's going to save us
some time here is we're going to copy
and duplicate the web server portion
because it's going to be the exact same
but now instead of web server this is
going to be the scheduler so it it
literally is going to be the exact same
so I don't think we need to change
anything no so the scheduler is a needed
worker for airflow and so we absolutely
need both of these one the web server to
give us a UI to access and then we're
also going to need the scheduler to
schedule all of our jobs here and
they're going to point to the same exact
thing okay so that is going to be the
setup for airflow now let's go into
writing our first dag in order to
actually orchestrate all of our tasks
here okay so we're going to go into our
dags folder here and we're going to
create a new folder and in that folder
is going to be
eltor dag dopy so we're going to be
writing some python here now the first
things we're going to import are going
to be from date time import date time
and time Delta so we're going to be
using some time values here and the next
one is going to be obviously airflow so
airflow uh from airflow we're going to
import D this is going to be a default
one that we're going to need because uh
obviously we need to type our dag from
Docker do types we're going to import
Mount this is going to come in handy for
us later because we're orchestrating
Docker services or Docker containers you
need some specific Docker types and then
we're also going to need a specific
Docker operator that comes from airflow
in order to actually orchestrate them uh
the next thing we're going to need is
going to be uh from airflow. operators.
python operator we going to import the
python
operator so this is going to be very
very crucial because our elt script is a
python script we need the python
operator in order to actually add that
in there okay so we're going to copy and
paste this down here as well because in
the same operators package we're going
to need the bash operator we're going to
change this to bash operator so that way
we can actually interact with the bash
here and and do a couple commands there
last one we're going to do it's going to
be from airflow actually should be copy
copying this again so from there we're
going to say Docker underscore or I
think it's just Docker here yeah just
Docker and then the docker operate cool
so these are all the packages oh
actually we're going to need one more
sub process silly me okay so those are
going to be all the packages that we
need here now let's go into some default
arguments here so we're going to see
default unor args um this is just couple
things so the owner of this whole
project here is going to be airflow the
next one is going to be depends on past
so do we want this to depends underscore
onore pass we're going to say false on
this so it doesn't email on failure
these are just some things that are
built into airflow and we are setting
some default values here default
arguments we're going to say false and
then on email uncore onore
retry I think these should be curly
brackets not square brackets I screw up
on that one cool all right now we're
going to write a function here Define
runor _ scripts so this is going to be a
function we use in order to actually run
the script now we're going to need the
script path obviously script scriptor
path we're going to set this variable
here and this is going to be pointed to
where we've set it inside of the docker
container so if you remember correctly
this path right here so we have opt
airflow
SLT so we need to point to that and not
where it's pointed to locally for us so
we're going to say SL optflow
slore script
Pi so now we are pointed directly to the
path of the elt script from within the
docker container so what we can do now
is we're going to say
result equals subprocess do run and this
is going to be you know we we've had
this command inside of actual batch
script itself so we're going to say
python we're going to run Python and
then we're going to use this point it to
the script path now after this we're
going to add a comma and we're going to
say capture output equals true so we
want to capture the output there and the
text equals true okay now after that
we're going to add a control structure
here so if
results. return code does not equal
doesn't equal zero that means we failed
something so we need to raise an
exception and in that we're going to say
script failed with error and then we're
going okay and then else we print the
result output cool now let's actually
put this into a dag so we're going to
say dag equals and then point it to the
dag object that we just imported add a
parenthesis and this is where we add in
all the information so the first one is
going to be the name so we're going to
name it elore andore DBT so that's going
to be the name of our tag now uh the
default arguments this is where it comes
into play here so we're going to say
default arguments equals the default
arguments that we've specified the
description of this dag is going to be
an elt workflow with DBT right
accidentally the start date start
underscore date is going to be date time
so that's where we're going to use date
time here and we're going to say
2023 uh it the time of this recording is
currently October 28th so that's going
to be our start time there catchup is
going to be another one catch up equals
pulse we're we're not going to catch up
all right oh I didn't close it I'm done
so now we're going to go into actually
writing out the tasks so you can name a
task whatever you want the first thing
I'm going to do or the easiest way to do
it for me is going to say T1 for task
one that's just the way I like to do it
and we're going to use the python
operator because the first task we want
is the elt script and because it is a
python script we need the python
operator now let's do the same thing
where we initiated the dag here where
we're going to add a parenthesis the
task ID is going to be task uncore ID
we're going to tag this over and you
know label this as runor elore script so
that we can identify this properly we're
going to say python column
equals the Run elt script function that
we just created and then the dag is
going to equal dag okay so very very
simple we've we've given it an
identifier we've added the python
function here in order for us to
actually run the elt script and then
we've attached it to the dag that we've
created all right the next one is going
to be task two which is going to be DBT
and obviously for DBT we've added the
docker operator so let's go ahead and
add all the necessary information
for the docker operator the same thing
is going to be here so task ID right uh
we're going to name this the same one is
going to be
DBT run very simple there after task ID
we're going to need to attach an image
to it and so um I we do have a DBT
container but we're actually going to
remove it and replace it with this so
we're going to do the same information
that we had in the docker or the DBT
container so we're going to say G
hc. DBT Labs DBT postgress for the
postgress adapter and then point it
directly to
1.4.7 all right and the command we're
going to run is going to be the exact
same so you can see kind of like the the
similarities here uh so we're going to
say that we're going to point it to the
profiles directory and the profiles
directory is going to be SL root the
project directory is going to b/ DBT and
then that should be it the next one for
this one is auto remove so Auto remove
is do we want to automatically remove
the container once it's finished and
we're going to say true because we don't
want it open all the time so Docker URL
is going to be the next one and this
we're going to be pointing directly to
the the socket that we open so Unix sl/
bar/ run/ doer. right it can identify
where of the docker container is now the
network mode we're going to label as
bridge and if you remember the docker or
the network driver for the docker
Network that we had was a bridge so that
is going to be our mode here and then
mounts so mounts is going to be where we
imported the type of mounts this is
where we're actually doing the same
thing that we see here in the DBT
service where we've mounted these two
volumes here and we want to mount them
because we're actually doing exactly
what we're doing here here but instead
we're doing it inside of airflow we're
creating this Docker container from
scratch using the same information but
that way airflow has sight of okay well
this is exactly what I'm orchestrating
let me go ahead and create this and then
run it so the first thing we're going to
do is say Mount and then inside of that
is going to be Source the source of this
is going to be the local path of my
actual custom postgress so I'm going to
say users SL my name is Justin Chow slev
development and this is going to be
separate and very different uh depending
on what you're doing here so the inside
of development is just the elt folder
and then we're going to go into custom
uncore post press is where my sources is
now after this we're going to say Target
equals slashin quotes SL DBT well that's
essentially mapping the source to the SL
DV folder and we're going to say type
equals bind okay now what we're going to
do is we're going to copy this and we're
going to add a comma here now this is
going to be shorter here so I can get
rid of pretty much everything here and
then we're going to say DBT because this
is our profile and then instead of
Target being SL DBT we want this to be
root and the type is going to remain
bind the last thing we need after the
mounts is going to tag it to the dag so
dag Dag
and there we go that's pretty much
writing both of our tasks the last thing
we need to do here is create the order
in which we want it to run and so at the
very bottom here we're going to say T1
two greater than signs and then T2 so
this means that T1 takes priority over
T2 and that's the order that we want it
to run in okay so let's go ahead and
make sure to save this it looks like we
have that's fine we don't have to worry
about this so that is pretty much
writing our dag here let's go over it
one more time we've created some default
arguments here that airflow needs inside
of the dag we've created our python
function in order to correctly identify
where the script is and then we're going
to go ahead and run it with some error
checks here we've created the actual dag
itself and named it with the default
arguments description and then the start
time we've created the first task here
using the python operator given it an
identifier pointed the function we
created to it so that's what we know to
run and then we've attached it to the
dag we created and then this is the
second operator or the second task here
using the docker operator and
essentially creating DBT in a new
container and then running and mounting
everything we need to correctly have you
know the DBT project run on top of the
destination once the first task has run
and then we've created the order of
operations here in which we want it to
run so hopefully this all makes sense in
this next one we're going to go ahead
and run it and show you what the web
server looks like and then make sure
that the dag actually works so let's get
into that okay so we have our dag now
the one thing to note is that we are
actually running the script here and
then creating a new Docker container
here for TBT so we can actually go back
into our Docker compos file and we're
going to comment out the DBT as well as
the elt script containers because we do
not need to create them anymore because
we have airflow doing it we don't need
to have them any so let's go ahead and
comment those out and what we're
actually going to do is we're going to
do docker compose up and run all these
containers so I forgot to do one thing
so remove the port section and then the
command should be scheduler not web
server that's my bad so let's do Docker
compose up again ports must
exist there we go okay just some weird
issue there so this is airflow
initializing everything everything seems
to be going into plan here and so now
what we can do exit with Code Zero we
should see the scheduler and the web
server pop up in just a second here oh
you know what okay so now that we have
everything going let's go ahead and
create all of our Docker compos files so
but the first thing we have to do is
actually run the init airflow container
first because it's very important so
we're going to say Docker compose up and
knit hyphen airflow and we're going to
actually say hyphen D in order to do
that first so what that's going to do is
going to start the postgress and it's
going to start the initialized airflow
containers first and if we go to Docker
desktop here you you can see that they
they're already running we actually need
those to be running first before we
enable anything else because without
those the web server and the scheduler
will not work so now what we can do is
we're going to say Docker compose up and
that's going to create the rest of the
docker containers that we have and so
let's go ahead and wait for that now we
can see that the web server is now open
so what I'm going to do here is going to
do open a new window and then we're
going to go to Local Host and remember
we said 8080 so if we go to Local Host
8080 we are now in the airflow UI so
airflow password was the username and
password that we enabled here we're
going to say no here no but you can see
we have an issue opt airflow dags
_
D.P a broken dag so that's fine I think
what we probably forgot to do was
install the python operators so let's go
ahead and debug this really quickly a
nothing like like a little bit of
problem right so let's just make sure op
airflow. oper python oper oh so this
should be an operator not operators now
let's go ahead and go back and kill all
of these again so Docker compose
down D we're going to say the same thing
so we're going to say Docker
compose let that run for a second and
then Docker compose up okay let's go
back to our web server here should load
up in just a second go airflow
password in I may have tried a little
too soon there we go uh we're still
running into an error here docker's the
operator I think I probably did this
let's look at the docker file here tip
install
Apache I an airflow
high do okay so I found the issue it was
from the actual package here so I wasn't
doing it properly on the docker file
here Pache airflow Pro Docker so this
should actually be airflow. providers.
doer uh and then operators. doer so that
should be the import name uh that's why
we were getting the issue here uh so
we're going to say Docker compos down B
do the same thing here end it airflow
wait a couple seconds then Docker
compose up in a second now hopefully
this should fix the issue because I had
another just like simple
typo so if we go back now crash airflow
password still the same issue oh I had
it twice it's another typo okay so this
shouldn't be operators this should be
providers A okay
compose down
I do initialize it again do compose up
again just some simple simple typos that
are screwing it all up there we go now
now that I haven't typoed anything you
can see that we have the elt and DBT dag
here we have the owner being airflow we
have all the runs um so you have failed
running success cued you have a schedule
your last run next run which we pointed
out would be today but we're going to go
ahead and manually run this so what
we're going to do is they're actually
going to trigger the dag and what we're
going to see here is we're going to see
it run so we see one is one is uh still
queued so we we have one successful and
I believe we should be waiting for one
more to go believe we're still waiting
for one more to go yeah okay so we see
one has failed now let's go ahead and
check why um so the dbt1 failed DBT was
not running at the state so we can check
the logs here now remember that we
created that DBT or sorry that postgress
service for the airf flow and so that is
because of this so we needed the actual
postgress database for this reason so we
can actually get some logs here if you
didn't have it it wouldn't we wouldn't
get any logs here so it's actually
erroring out because custom post. myc
DBT model depends on a node name my
first DBT model which was not found
which is interesting because this is not
what we had in mind here very
interesting so it looks like the script
worked but the DVT section did not so
we're going to have to take a look at
why and it has to be something in here
right so the DVT run profiles directory
profiles directory is going to be/ root
project directory is going to be SL DVD
if we check the docker desktop we go
into web server go into files here um
and then I believe so rout should
contain our DBT folder with the
profiles. yl folder and we can actually
see that custom post address has exactly
the information we're looking for so
that's root that is fine the other one
that we should have airflow x no airflow
where did we put the actual we put in SL
DBT so let's go back it should be in a
DBT but it is not SL op SL D and I
believe our models should be in here
okay so I think we're pointing it to the
wrong area here so SL opt SL DVT let's
go ahead and see if that changes
everything cuz we didn't create
the section there so let's go ahead and
restart this so we're going to
say airflow wait a second
okay let's go back to the UI password
okay this is still going let's go ahead
and Trigger it okay I think we're still
waiting on one one's running right now
which is a good thing let's hope it
doesn't fail fails now let's go ahead
and Che the logs here there inv valid
project directory not a project project
AML okay so that's a better sign which
means that we just need to change this
now slash op slash now I believe that
when we run this it should work let's go
ahead and kill this same
thing go up should be good reset go
ahead and run it so looks like the elt1
ran successfully and then we're just
going to wait for the second one to pass
hopefully it does and it's still failing
why is it still pointing to the other
models I don't know how this happened
but inside of the example folder there
was a my second DBT model sequel file
that was throwing the eror so I just
deleted it so now let's try and see if I
don't know how that got in there I I
don't even remember if I deleted or not
but obviously while we were testing it
manually it wasn't throwing an error but
now airflow decides to throw the error
so let's go ahead and see if that's
going to fix the issue I'm pretty sure
it will very just like didn't even think
about it kind of thing but again like
I'm leaving all these mistakes in there
not because it's like obviously doesn't
look that great but I do believe that
these errors are just a part of
Engineering in general and so I think
it's good to put some light on it and
just you know not every course or not
every lesson is going to be fully
fledged I think it's better to just
leave that stuff in there because you
know we all go through mistakes stuff
like this happens where it just you know
there was one file that was throwing
everything off or something like that
now let's go ahead and see if I can
actually get in here so I can refresh
and I'm in so let me go ahead and hit
start on the dag and let's see what we
get here so it looks like our batch
script worked now we're just waiting for
airflow let's hope for for number two on
the green I think we're still running
cool that was it that was literally it
so now you can see we have two on the
success part so we have our DBT and our
elt script that ran successfully so what
we can do now is we can go into our
destination postest and do the
destination
DB and we're going to say/ DT and you
can see all the models and everything
that we ran are now inside of the
destination and to prove that I can say
select all from
uh let's say specific movie again and
you can see that the Inception selection
is still there I can say select all from
users and everything should be in there
so that is successfully adding airflow
with some minor hiccups but obviously
you can see here that our python
operator and our Docker operator are in
play here and working it does take a
little bit of work to make sure that
everything is moving because there yes
there is a lot of moving Parts here but
in this next section with the elt script
we're making it a lot easier because
we're removing the need for the elt
script we're actually adding in another
open source tool that I happen to work
for called air bites to be able to add
more Integrations and more data sources
more destinations with ease so let's
look at how that would work with
orchestration and everything like that
all put together now all right so for
this next and final section like I
mentioned we're going to be implementing
an open-source data integration tool
called air B which I just so happen to
work for airite we are pretty much a
data Movement platform like I just said
so you have a bunch of sources like we
have our source database and we have our
destination database both in postgress
now imagine you have a couple other
sources that aren't just postgress but
you also have places like Salesforce or
LinkedIn Facebook marketing places like
that where you need data to come out of
and then move them into you know your
destination postgress database or you
may have some cloud data warehouses
things like that air bite is the
platform to easily sync all of them
together without having to manage any of
these manual scripts like the one we
just made use a dump file to go from
postest to postgress uh it would be much
more complicated if we were doing that
from you know a different source to a
different destination and so I'm going
to show you how easy it is to get airite
into your project and it's open source
like I said and utilizes Docker so it's
pretty easy to hook up to the rest of
our application and then get airflow
hooked up as well so let's go ahead and
do that so I am on the air bite repo
right now which you can just go on
GitHub and all we're going to do pretty
simply is just copy this uh what we're
going to do is we're going to go back
into our terminal here we're going to
stop all of the docker containers and
then what we're going to do is get clone
and then we're going to clone air bite
into our repo here so that's going to
take a little bit the big open source
package and then if you wanted to read
the read me on how to get started and
things like that all of it is down here
but you can see that literally like you
can use this project for free and that's
the beauty of Open Source right so now
if we hit LS you can see we've created
an airite directory here and if we open
our project here on vs code you can see
that airite is now successfully inside
of the file directory along with
everything else so now let's hook up
everything together to make sure that it
works in harmony but before we run
anything with air bite we actually got
to set up a couple things so we do not
need to touch this Docker compos file
anymore that is completely all set and
ready to go if we go into this Docker
file you can see that obviously we've
installed the docker provider we're
actually going to install the air bite
provider as well as a couple other
things uh yes like I mentioned that
there are a couple other Integrations
with airf flow and air bite is one of
them with open source it's a little
different but we do use the HTTP
provider as well as the airb provider so
we're going to change this command up a
little bit everything's going to stay
the same but when we run pip install the
provider's docker we're going to add a
little uh Slash here we're going to say
and and pip
install Apache air flow providers and
then we're going to say HTTP we're going
add another backs slash here and we're
going to add another and and and then
this is going to be pip install Apache
airflow providers air bite so now we're
installing three different packages that
we need u i mean yes we do we do need
the docker one still but so yes we we're
going to be using airflow for Docker
HTTP and air bite works synonymously
together HTTP provider is a dependency
for the air provider so now we're going
to save that I'm actually going to
change up this
start.sh file so it's going to make it a
little bit easier to run the whole
project Al together we don't have to
keep waiting for the init air flow to
start and then we can kind of structure
the way that all these Zer containers
are running with this bash script so let
me go ahead and do that right now okay
so we're going to actually delete all
this stuff that's in here right now the
first thing that we want to do is we
want to do Docker compose up and then we
want to do in air flow now that's going
to obviously do the initialization of
air flow after that we're going to wait
5 seconds so we're going to sleep the
command for 5 seconds and then next
we're going to say Docker compose up hph
D to run it in the background because if
we don't run it in the background we
can't really um continue to see air bite
come through so after that we're going
to sleep for another 5 seconds after
that we're going to change directories
into the air bites directory because if
we see it here you can well you don't
you won't see it now but there is a
Docker composed file that needs to be
downloaded here and that's exactly what
we're going to do so we're going to CD
into airite and we're going to do a
little check here because the way that
we run it is there's a run platform uh
shell script that we need to run with
airite and that is the initialization
where it downloads all the correct files
that we need to in order to spin up all
the docker containers so we're going to
say if and we're going to look for the
file here so we're going to say uh
hyphen f and then we're looking for
Docker composed. yo that's the file
we're looking for if
that exists then we're going to uh run
Docker compos up hyphen D if it doesn't
exist we're going to run slash run
hyphen ab
platform.sh and then we're going to
finish okay so very simple script here
uh we're also going to create another
one that's going to say stop. sh so this
one is going to say Docker compose down
hyphen V and then we're going to uh I
think we're going to sleep for 5 seconds
we're going to CD into air bite and and
then do Docker compose down so that is
going to be the start and stop for this
to make this easier to run every single
container so now what we're going to do
we're going to go into our dag and then
change up everything because we no
longer need this elt script we're
obviously going to still need the docker
operator but the python operator we
don't need it anymore since we're going
to be using airite to do it so let's go
ahead and
hook that up right now all right so like
I said we we actually didn't end up
using the bash operator and we don't
need the python operator anymore so we
can remove this um let's go ahead and
remove the time Delta as well because we
do not need that right now so what we're
going to do is also remove this function
here and then this is where we're going
to start doing our actually I'm going to
leave this for now so right here above
the default args we're going to create a
Conor ID variable and this is going to
be a string so this will make sense so a
connection ID is what this stands for
within airite we have a connection ID
and a workspace ID and those are just
identifiers for your specific instance
of airite let's say but more
specifically if we're looking at the
source and the destination that we
currently have the both of the postgress
databases connecting those together
obviously create a connection and for
airite when we connect the two we have a
connector and that connector has that
connection ID so that's exactly what
we're going to use this variable for is
to grab that and then input it here into
the Dag to make sure that we're
orchestrating the correct connector
right now and so here what we're going
to do is we're actually going to go back
up here we're going to say from airflow
uh the first thing we're actually going
to do is from utils and dates so we're
going to use the dates util from airflow
we're going to import days uncore ago
under that we're going to say from
airflow. providers. a. operators. airite
we're going to import the airite trigger
sync operator so this is going to be the
module that we're using to trigger syns
on the connection that we create with
from within airbag now we're going to
replace that replace T1 with this
operator here let's go ahead and replace
it and now the first thing we're going
to do is change the task ID so this is
uh oh whoops I replaced the wrong one uh
this is the python operator we're trying
to replace so the first thing we're
going to replace is the task ID so this
one is going to be the Airy _ postgress
_ postgress task ID and uh we no longer
have a python callable here but the
first thing we're going to do is
aircore Conor ID which is an argument
that we need which obviously we've
provided which is going to be air bite
so this will make more sense once we're
inside of web flow but we need to make a
connection inside airflow and we're
going to name that air bite so we're
going to add that the connection ID is
what we provided so this will point to
the con ID variable that we had right
make sure that my commas here underneath
that is asynchronous so if we wanted to
asynchronously do jobs asynchronous I
think is how I spell it wait did I spell
that right asynchronous false so this is
not going to be asynchronous we would
have to add another operator but we're
not doing any jobs asynchronously we're
only triggering one job so we're going
to leave it at that we're going to leave
the timeout to 3600 we're going to say
waitor seconds uh we're going to wait 3
seconds and then the dag obviously we're
we're putting back into deck so you can
see pretty simple in terms of what it's
accepting here the main thing here to
note is going to be these two properties
right here so the airb con ID which
we're going to find within airflow and
then the connection ID is going to be
what's important to us here so we're
actually going to save that and nothing
else changes so we've we've successfully
put an air bite within the dag um the
one thing we need to do here is we do
need to add our connection ID which we
have not gotten yet there is a little
bit of a trick here that we're going to
have to do um it's kind of inefficient
but for the sake of this project we're
going to have to do it so let me show
you what that is we're going to have to
make another bash script potentially but
it should all be okay this is what
happens when you kind of have to work
with multiple different Docker
containers since airite is working in in
its own so let's go ahead and do that
right now I'm actually going to create
another bash script here um this one's
going to be elt Dosh and this one is
going to be exactly what we did before
where it's just Docker compose up init
uh hyphen airflow and then we're going
to sleep for five and then we're going
to Docker compose up Hy so the reason
for this is that air bite has its own
set of do containers that are running to
make sure that everything is working and
then we have our own elt containers that
we've already been working with and we
can close those separately now in order
for this to work we need to grab the
connection ID that we make from within
air bite and in order to create the
connection we need to obviously hook up
the source and the destination together
which we're going to do next but then
when we have the connection ID we can't
necessarily save the connection ID into
the dag and then you know load it up
we're going to have to kill the
container so that the new connector ID
propagates but air bite will still be
active so we're just going to go ahead
and kind of go through that process but
then at the end we'll see that airflow
is able to read everything that we've
done and then we can orchestrate both
air bites that's replacing our elt
script and then using DBT to write on
top of the destination databases that we
have currently so let's go ahead and run
air bite right now and then we'll get
going into uh hooking up both of the
source and destinations to create our
first connector all right so now we're
in the UI and then now all we got to do
is put in our information here you can
choose this if you want but I'm going to
say get started and then now we're in
the airb UI and let me walk you through
really quickly it's it's very simple so
we have connections so if you have all
your sources and destinations in they're
connected together this would be your
connections if we go to sources you can
see we have a bunch of different sources
both certified as well as community and
the same thing on the destination side
so the one thing we're going to do is
we're actually going to go for post
crust here you can see it's pretty
simple it's just simply logging in to
your instances here or our databases so
I'm actually going to name this source
postgress and then for the host here
we're going to say host. Docker do
internal and for the port I believe Port
5433 is is the name or is the port
number and then for the database name is
going to be Source DB now for the
username was just postgress and for the
password was just secret okay now no SSL
modes no SSH tunnels needed for this
sake I'm going to be using detect
changes with the X-Men system column and
then you know if you have any jdbc URL
parameters here you can absolutely add
that let me go ahead and hit set up
Source here and then it should just
essentially make a call to the postest
database there through the API and We're
Off to the Races it should just connect
properly if everything is correct and if
I look on Docker we should have the
containers open so that is correct cool
all the test connections have passed so
then it spits us over to create a
connection and we're actually going to
add a destination now which is going to
be also postgress now it's going to be
the same thing we're going to name this
destination
postgress uh host. doer. internal the
port here is going to be 5434 DB name is
going to be
destination DB default schema uh we're
going to name the user postgress and
then it's kind of hidden right now but
in the optional Fields we're going to
say secret as the password because we do
need that and then we're going to go
ahead and hit setup destination and cool
all test connections have passed and
what you can see up here uh is that we
have you know the connection name you
have source postgress to destination
postgress replication frequency there
isn't orchestrator from within airite
but we want to switch this over to
manual because we are orchestrating this
with airflow if we were wanted to just
have this work on its own we can
absolutely do that if we wanted to add a
Kon job you can absolutely do that as
well from within here but for our sake
we're going to use manual there's a name
space there's the stream prefix to
identify streams a little easier and
here is all the tables coming in from
our source database now what I'm going
to do here is I'm going to check all of
these cuz I want all of these streams or
all of these tables to come with and now
from here we can choose a sync mode so
do we want to fully refresh every single
time do we want to incremental which we
recommend uh only the changes because it
does support CDC do we only want to sync
the changes from the database over to
the destination depending on the
transactions uh in our case we're going
to do full refresh overwrite for all of
them uh so we can do some uh testing
here but uh yes incremental sync is
probably the way to go here we do offer
normalized tabular data in this so we do
some normalization on top of the data
and that is totally fine so I'm going to
go ahead and set up this connection here
and there we go uh once this is all set
up we can see here at the top we have we
have a couple IDs that are very
important to us so the first one is
going to be the workspaces ID uh the
next one is going to be the connections
ID we want this connections ID so what
we're going to do is copy this head over
into our dag and paste this into the
connection I now we're going to save
this but remember what I said when we uh
you know when we launch airflow and and
all of these containers right here
they're in separate instances right and
so the change just made has not
propagated and so we're not going to be
able to stop or to start the dag right
now so what we're going to do is we're
actually going to kill the elt section
first and then leave airite open restart
this we should be able to then start the
sink using airflow so what I'm going to
do now is Docker compose up or uh we
have that elt script so what I'm going
to do is I have to add uh see sod plus
x/t Dosh and now I can say elt
Dosh and that should run the init first
and then that should run the rest of the
docker containers we need on the elt
side um so the init is done and we can
see it down here and then it should
follow up with all of that so there we
go everything should be initialized now
what we have to do is obviously
everybody is still running now let's go
in and do Local Host port 8080 that's
going to let us sign into our instance
here uh we're having an issue with the
dag uh I think it's the provider here
yep okay so I had an issue with this
before airflow. providers. a. operators.
Airy um let me double check to make sure
that is the correct installation of it
so what we're probably going to need to
do is for some reason this doesn't fully
work here use your airflow yeah because
we let me double check this um oh I
forgot to do that okay so the one thing
we do actually need to do is we need to
remove this user tag here because we
want the user to switch every single
time so uh we it's a weird thing where
you have to be the airflow user before
to install the actual correct operator
and then switch back to the route in
order to run the dag so that's what
we're going to do we're going to do
Docker compose down hyphen B um and then
run our elt script again after we remove
that so let's go ahead and run it should
be good so then it will use it'll go
down and read the user airflow first run
this command to install all the correct
operators and then we'll have back to
the user route once they're installed
that way we can actually run the dag
okay so that should be good let me go
ahead and wait for it to run here there
we go uh still having an error here all
right so I got it working and this is
just a note uh there is some weird
issues kind of with Docker but so if you
ever run into issues like that you want
to go into the images section so I had
to look for for the elt web server and
scheduler because we built those images
already and it doesn't propagate with
these new commands here and so when I
reran or sorry when I deleted the images
and reran it it actually went through
and installed the correct operator so
now if we go back to the web UI you can
see that the dag is now in there so we
did everything correctly it was just a
matter of deleting the images on Docker
first and so now what we're going to do
is before we even run it we need to go
up into connections uh and then hit this
plus sign right here and now what we can
see is we have a connection type of air
bite but that's not exactly what we're
going to be using so if you remember
this connection ID if we go back to the
code of the dag you can see we had a
connection IDE of airbit so what we're
going to do is we're going to say air
bites we're going to go down into uh
HTTP and then for the host is going to
be do uh host. doer. internal we don't
need to provide login password but for
the UI we're actually going to point it
to 801 because that's going to be where
um we can access access the actual UI
and everything so we're going to hit
save and so now we have this air bite
section if we go back to dags let's go
ahead and Trigger this and so we
triggered it if we go back to the airb
connections we should be able to refresh
and hopefully see that a stream is going
to start here eventually okay so it
failed instantly okay so it looks like
it aired because let's actually go back
to the uh the connections here we
actually may need to do a login password
so this is host. doer. internal 801
let's add airb
and password because this is a default
um thing that's needed or login that's
needed for us on our side uh for
security reasons and obviously that can
change let me go ahead and rerun this
again and that should give us
permissions to run the sync there we go
so now you can see that we have a sync
running so we've able to trigger the
actual sync Now using airflow and that
should just work so if we go back to
statuses here we should be able to watch
it go and then once that's loaded into
to the destination then the DBT
container will spin up and then we will
have all of our models written onto the
destination side but data was moved from
Air bite so let's go ahead and wait for
that to load here but if we go back to
the dags we can see that it's all
working now we were able to successfully
connect to airbit and it's not going to
succeed until this is completely done
there we go so sink has succeeded you
can see that we have3 records extracted
if we go back to airflow we should be
able to see that it will will succeed
and then it's going to run DBT uh there
we go so there's the first success and
then now we're waiting for DBT to run
and then once DBT has run we're going to
go ahead and check so DBT just
successfully ran go back into our
terminal and then go back into our
destination database so see
destination DB let's go ahead and do a
/dt and then you can see so now we have
some extra stuff so you can see airb
actually wrote some raw data into the
database but it has come with all of the
other tables here notice how specific
movie and film ratings isn't here so you
can see that DBT actually ran we only
have the tables coming from the source
database and now if we do select all
from specific
movie that's going to show the actual
Inception you know all that stuff along
with some airite metadata so you could
see that has actually successfully
worked we have air bite being
orchestrated by airflow and DBT now
being or rated by airflow all within
this simple project and that right there
is the full project completed hopefully
that give you a pretty high level
understanding and example of how you
could successfully create a data
pipeline from scratch but then
ultimately lead that into a
fully-fledged open-source data pipeline
where you're sending data from a
postgress database using a tool like
airite to connect it to a destination
database where you need the data to go
to and then from there you're
orchestrating it with airflow writing
custom models on top of it with DBT to
then use for other sort of data analysis
or things like that ultimately the
destination could be anything where it
ends up in a CRM or some sort of tool
like metabase or looker for other open-
source options there but essentially
this is kind of like my version of a
storytelling where you can see how a
data pipeline can evolve how complicated
it can be at the very beginning but then
how simple it can be at the very end
when you start using some of the tools
in the modern data stack where you know
you have tools like air bite and airflow
and many other tools where you can bring
into the stack and just make it a lot
easier as a data engineer now the
opportunities here are endless and this
is can hopefully open some doors to you
to test some things and also play around
with other things to become a data
engineer eventually but please let us
know how we did please let me know if
you have any questions or if you learned
anything new here please let me know
down in the comments or anything like
that but I hope you all enjoyed this
course and thank you so much for
watching